<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Two homilies concerning the meanes how to resolue the controversies of this time. First written in French, by Ph. Mornay, and now translated into English</title>
            <title>Deux homélies du moyen de se résoudre sur les controverses de ce temps. English</title>
            <author>Mornay, Philippe de, seigneur du Plessis-Marly, 1549-1623.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1612</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 125 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 73 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07787</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18164</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112907</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848148</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848148</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13226</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07787)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13226)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1211:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Two homilies concerning the meanes how to resolue the controversies of this time. First written in French, by Ph. Mornay, and now translated into English</title>
                  <title>Deux homélies du moyen de se résoudre sur les controverses de ce temps. English</title>
                  <author>Mornay, Philippe de, seigneur du Plessis-Marly, 1549-1623.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 138 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Ioseph Barnes,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1612.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Deux homélies du moyen de se résoudre sur les controverses de ce temps.</note>
                  <note>A variant of the edition omitting the author's name from the title page.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13226:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13226:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>TWO HOMILIES CONCERNING the meanes how to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolue the controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies of this time.</p>
            <p>Firſt written in French, by <hi>Ph. Mornay,</hi> and now tranſlated into Engliſh.</p>
            <p>AT OXFORD, Printed by Ioſeph Barnet 1612.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:13226:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13226:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>THou haſt here (gentle Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) two homilies (for ſo the authour himſelfe, whoſoever hee bee, entitleth them) written firſt in French, and now for thine vnderſtanding tranſlated into Engliſh. Two homilies indeed ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry neceſſary in theſe times, not on<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly for the authours countrymen and ſuch like, who liue amongſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Papiſts, but alſo for vs of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, amongſt whom it is to be fea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red too too many Papiſts do lurk. The authour by his writing ſhews himſelfe to be <hi>a French-man, &amp; that a true, religious, &amp; zealous Proteſtant, a French ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> he may be thought to be becauſe he writs in french: as alſo the ſame may be gathered out of his ſecond homily wherein in ſome two or three pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces he speaketh according to the diſcipline of the reformed French<note place="margin">P. 84. &amp; 134.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:13226:3"/>Churches, which haue no Biſhops over them, and wherein no clergy man hath any temporall iuriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. <hi>A Proteſtant</hi> he is, for how would he elſe haue thus writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the errours of the Romiſh church? &amp; that <hi>a true, religious and zealous one;</hi> for how coulde hee elſe haue written them vvith ſuch earneſtnes, and ſoundnes of doctrine? The homelies the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues need not be comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded vnto thee; they will commend the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently, if thou wilt but take the paines to read the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> over adviſedly. Farewell.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="homily">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:13226:3"/>
            <head>HVNC AVDITE Matth. <hi>17.</hi> v. <hi>5.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>OV Chriſtians, that are perplex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in your minds amidſt the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies of this time, hovering betweene the choice of that which is Diuine, &amp; that which is humane, of that which is Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenticall, and that which is A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocryphal, of that which is true and that which ſeemes to bee true, two only words out of the holy Goſpell are able to put you out of doubt, and to cauſe you to ſee the difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene them. And behold, here
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:13226:4"/>is one of them for you; <hi>Hunc au dite, Heare him.</hi> Him, and no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Our Lord Ieſus had nowe take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> apart three of his diſciples, <hi>Peter, Iames,</hi> &amp; <hi>Iohn,</hi> &amp; brought the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vp into an high mountain. There had hee beene transfigu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red before them, his face ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning as the Sun, his cloathes being beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e as white as ſnowe. which in this baſenes were as pledges of his future glorie, of that glorie, which hee tooke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, when it pleaſed him, and which hee had neuer put away. There were <hi>Moſes</hi> &amp; <hi>Elias</hi> ſeene by his diſciples talking with him <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets: as in a manner giuing up there charge into his hands. his indeed which was the marke and the end, the perfection and accompliſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t both of the law &amp; the Prophets. Here Peter comes in, as it were, in oppoſition, <hi>Maſter it is good
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:13226:4"/>for vs to be here.</hi> Being already raviſhed and drunken with the ſhew of this glory, &amp; theſe ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall delightes. <hi>Let vs make here three Tabernacles, one for thee, and one for Moſes, and one for Elias.</hi> And we doubt not, but in this firſt he reſerued a roome for himſelfe and his fellow-diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples. But as he ſpake, and <hi>knew not,</hi> ſaith both S. <hi>Mark</hi> and S. <hi>Luke, what he ſaid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mar. 9. v. 6 Luc. 9.</note> God from heauen directed him. Out of a cloud, that ſhadowed them, came a voice ſaying, <hi>This is that my beloued ſonne, in whome I am well pleaſed, Heare him.</hi> No lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger Moſes, no longer Elias: the old things are come to an end; I bring you new tidings, good new tidings. There is here no longer any need of Tabernacles or that wee ſhould paſſe from one figure to another. She hath from henceforth a place where
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:13226:5"/>ſhee may reſt. She is to be built on the firme ground. Wilt thou Peter, wil yee, my diſciples, one day enioy this glory, and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe eternally that which you haue ſeene as in a glimpſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold here the meanes, the only means, to wit, my welbeloved, your happineſſe, and all my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light: But, <hi>Heare him.</hi> For it is he of whom Moſes, the ſame which you haue ſcene talking with him, which did here come to re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der homage vnto him for the whole law, told you heretofore very neere two thouſand yeares agoe. (See how the Lord fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth his ſayings in their due time,<note place="margin">Deut. 18.1.18.</note>) <hi>The Lord ſaid vnto mee, I will raiſe them vp a Prophet from amongſt their brethren, like vnto thee, and will put my words in his mouth, and hee ſhall speake vnto them all that I ſhall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand him: And whoſoever will not harken
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:13226:5"/>vnto my words, which hee ſhall speake in my name, I will require it of him.</hi> It is the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> profit to heare him, and daunger to turne the eare from him. It is he of whom I ſpake vnto you by Eſay my Prophet,<note place="margin">Eſay, 42. v 1.</note> 
               <hi>Behold my ſervant, hee is mine elect, I haue put my spirit vpon him.</hi> And do not ſtand vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his lowneſſe, or his humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in that he <hi>will not cauſe his voice to bee heard in the ſtreet,</hi> nor will not make much noiſe. For ſo much the rather ought you to harken vnto him; what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer you ſee him to be, yet he ſhall bring forth iudgement in truth. And is not that it which you ought to looke for in theſe daies? <hi>Hee ſhall not faile nor bee diſcouraged,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ, 4.</note> 
               <hi>til he haue ſet iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the earth:</hi> till he haue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed the whole world. Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, it is he of whom Iohn the Baptiſt, that Elias which you
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:13226:6"/>looked for, which you haue ſeene, ſpake vnto you in theſe daies: hee being not the worde made fleſh, vnto the which you ought at this time to harke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but the voice which cryeth in the wilderneſſe, the forerunner of this word. Not that light which lighteth every man that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth into the world, but a lamp that beareth witneſſe of that light. <hi>This is he of whom I ſaid, hee that commeth after mee was better the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I:</hi>
               <note place="margin">oh. 1.15.</note> 
               <hi>for he was before me.</hi> Before me, in as much as hee is <hi>the everlaſting word.</hi> After mee, in as much as hee is <hi>the vvord made fleſh.</hi>
               <note place="margin">V. 16.</note> 
               <hi>Of his fulneſſe haue al we receiued,</hi> Moſes, Elias, all the Prophets.<note place="margin">V. 17</note> 
               <hi>For the law was given by Moſes;</hi> the law that enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained vs with figures, vs euery one bound ouer alſo to ſinne, &amp; therefore to death; <hi>Grace and truth is come vnto you by Ieſus
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:13226:6"/>Chriſt.</hi> And againe therefore, <hi>Heare him:</hi> the rather truly, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>no man hath ſeene God at any time.</hi> No man can tell you any thing concerning diuine matters, concerning things that appertaine to your ſalvation, but by him: But the only ſonne, more then any other, and after another manner. For as much as he is from everlaſting in the <hi>bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome of the father.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 8.</note> From euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting and before all ages. That eternall wiſdome which was with him in the creation of all things, and in the which <hi>he took his delight.</hi> Shee which cryed ſo long agoe, <hi>Giue eare, for the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pening of my lips ſhal teach thing, that be right,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov 8. v. 6 &amp; 7.</note> 
               <hi>my mouth ſhal speak the truth.</hi> But at this time con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcending to our weakneſſe, made bone of your bones ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth vnto you mouth to mouth And therefore the Lord brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:13226:7"/>through the thicke cloude of all theſe precedent witneſſes ſpake thus vnto vs, (And who will not giue heede vnto this voice?) <hi>Heare it. Heare him.</hi> The Lorde then will haue his ſonne harkened vnto: Ieſus our Lord; his well beloued ſonne, harke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto, as being the teacher of ſaluation, but farther, let vs ſee by whom. It is ſaid, that hee had taken apart, Peter, Iohn, &amp; Iames, the cheefeſt among the Apoſtles, for to make them par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of that viſion, and by a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent of this leſſon; &amp; in their perſons ſo much the more all the reſt.<note place="margin">Gal. 2.9.</note> 
               <hi>Iames, Cephas, and Iohn,</hi> ſaith S. Paul, <hi>counted among the pillers of the Church.</hi> Taking the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for afoundatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their doctrine this leſſon, this word: Iames, &amp; Iohn, thoſe whome Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelft hath honoured with the name of <hi>Sennes of thunder,</hi> not
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:13226:7"/>being able to make a ſound, nor to thunder, but according to the voice, which hee giueth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Peter himſelfe, on whoſe confeſſion he built his Church; what greater honour could he receiue? Bound by his Apoſtle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip to heare him; to heare him for to teach it vnto others, and not any thing of his owne. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe being ſubiect to this Anathema pronounced by God; <hi>Whoſoever will not harken vnto my wordes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. v. 19.</note> 
               <hi>which hee ſhall speake in my name, I will require it of him.</hi> And to harken is to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey; for an Apoſtle and miniſter of the Goſpell, it is to cauſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to obey. An Anathema, which hath ſince been doubled and expounded by S. Paul euen in the cauſe of S. Peter.<note place="margin">Gal. 1. &amp; 9.</note> 
               <hi>Though that we, or an Angell from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, preach vnto you otherwiſe, then that which we hauepreached
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:13226:8"/>vnto you, let him be accurſed, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nathema.</hi> And indeed when the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, God through the heauen; all the Angels of heauen what haue they to gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay? Yea what can they ſay? Tou ching Gods matters, to ſpeake after God, after the ſon of God which was ſent and came down expreſly to declare them vnto vs? Who can doe this, but the king of pride, and the Angels of darkneſſe transformed into An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels of light?</p>
            <p>You wil ſay then, let vs heare him: but are you of opinion that wee ought to heare him alone? Yea truly, alone: For it is not without a myſtery, that it is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Evangeliſt, that <hi>as the voice was a speaking, Ieſus was left alone. Moſes</hi> and <hi>Elias</hi> beeing retired and giving him place; how much more al other reachers, all other men? And if
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:13226:8"/>it be forbidden ſo expreſlie vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſo high a paine to adde to or diminiſh from the law giuen by the miniſtery of Angels; howe much the rather is it forbidden concerning the Goſpell pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced by the mouth of the Son of God, light of light, the word, the everlaſting wiſdome of the Father, whoſe doctrine cannot chooſe but bee perfect, perpetual, eternall? Alone, more over, for who will be ſo preſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous, as to dare ſet hand to his workmanſhip, and after him to teachvs any way of ſalvation; to preſcribe vs any rule thereof: &amp; after him to diſcloſ vnto vs any miſtery of Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or any thing that might bee expedient for a heavenly life? Laſtly, alone, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there was but one Sonne, whom it behoved to ſet an end to all the Law givers of Iuda: &amp; one Prophet by excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce poiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:13226:9"/>out to <hi>Moſes,</hi> by who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God might reveale himſelfe to the world &amp; ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto vs the depths of his iuſtice and of his mercie. <hi>This Chriſt,</hi> ſaid the Samaritan woman,<note place="margin">Ioh 4.25.</note> 
               <hi>which when he is come, will tell vs all things.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaith this voice from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven vnto vs, <hi>Hunc audite,</hi> poin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting him vnto vs as it were with a finger, <hi>heare him.</hi> Him alone, whom ſo many former ages, ſo many herald, haue gon before, &amp; haue continually by ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion preached vnto you: if that wee ought to haue learned the way of ſalvation from any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, by what path ſo euer hee brought vs thereunto, to what purpoſe then neede wee haue come vnto him, vnto him alone without interruption ever ſince the beginning of the world? if any one might put in never ſo ſmal an helping hand with him:
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:13226:9"/>to what end then is it, that the law and the Prophets doe aime at him alone; that <hi>Moſes</hi> &amp; <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as</hi> were ſwallowed vp in him, &amp; vaniſhed out of ſight before him? This furniture of glory, this voice from heauen, God in his owne perſon being preſent at this charge, was al this for to tell vs ſome thing either com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon or communicable to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? Heare him, my well belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved ſonne; Him, in whom I am well pleaſed, but for this time only, but without preiudice to them that ſhall come after, but with a reſeruatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of other rules of well beleeuing, and well do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, which ſhall from time to time be taught vnto you; but if the meaning had bin, that they ſhoulde haue reſted here, was there any need of this ſolemne tranſfiguration, of ſo maieſtical a preface? As therefore when <hi>S.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:13226:10"/>Iohn</hi> ſaith vnto vs of <hi>Ieſus; Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the Lambe of God;</hi> we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider in this Lambe all the typi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call and Sacramentall Lambes both ended and, accompliſhed: after this Lambe, we do no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger ſettle our mindes and hopes vpon any other, that can take away or beare the ſinnes of the world. In like manner, and that farre more ſtrictly, when God here ſaith vnto vs, <hi>heare him;</hi> This <hi>Ieſus,</hi> this <hi>Chriſt,</hi> this Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manuel, God with vs, my well beloued long before promiſed, at this day exhibited, the tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher of ſaluation, the author of life, &amp; that by his death for vs. Let vs thinke, that in this Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, in this Lawgiuer al others are accompliſhed and take an end: let no man preſume ſo far, as to bring his lampe into the Chriſtian church, if he haue not lighted it at the beames of this
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:13226:10"/>Sunne, all humane inuentions and rules being ſet aſide; as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore times all ſtrange fire was farre from the Lords Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, from his altar, from the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer, from the Prieſt, on paine of being deuoured.</p>
            <p>A ſtrange concluſion, will ſome man here ſay vnto vs, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted by ſo many poſitiue laws, by ſo many new examples, &amp; ſo many good rules. We will there fore let him heare the Fathers. <hi>Tertullian; Let vs then hear him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tertul. l. 3. adverſ. Marcioné cap. 22.</note> 
               <hi>of whom God had from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning declared that he ought to be heard in the name of a Prophet, becauſe that for ſuch an one hee was to bee eſteemed among the people.</hi> But was he alone ſo to be eſteemed? <hi>S. Cyprian Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lians</hi> ſcholler, and which verie likely had learned if from him, ſaith. <hi>That wee ought to heare Chriſt alone, the father hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:13226:11"/>it from heave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſaying,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cypr<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ad Cicil. de ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Dom. ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licis Ep. 63 in edit Pamelia na.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c. Heare him. Wherfore if we ought to heare Chriſt alone, then ought wee not to minde, what an other ſhall thinke fit to bee done before vs, but what Chriſt the firſt of all, which is before all, hath done; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe alſo we ought not to followe the cuſtomes of men, but the truth of God.</hi> And to the ſame purpoſe doth hee bring in many places out of the holy Scriptures both before and after. The reaſon thereof is to be ſound in <hi>S. Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ambr. de fide l. 1. c. 5.</note> Becauſe that <hi>no man com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to the Father, but by the So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, be it what it will that thou medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tateſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the Father.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chryſoſt Homil 57 in Matth.</note> And likewiſe <hi>thou ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt think nothing touching divine matters, but by the Sonne.</hi> Wherevpon <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi> ſaith, <hi>Heare him in all things.</hi> In all, without exception; <hi>that from hence forth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hiero Matt. 6.17</note> ſaith <hi>S. Hierome, we might no more pitch anie taberna
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:13226:11"/>cle but to him, obey none but him,</hi> no lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger <hi>Moſes,</hi> nor <hi>Elias; they are but ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts; it is no leſſe their dutie then ours, to raiſe him up a tabernacle within their hearts.</hi> He that ſpake thus of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, what would he haue ſaide of ſuch as are com ſince? of all thoſe foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of new orders? vnto which notwithſtanding we erect as well as to Chriſt, yea in ſome ſort aboue Chriſt, temples, al tars, and ſacrifices: and obey the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> rather the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the law, the Goſpell, or the Sonne of God himſelfe.</p>
            <p>But paſſe we this ouer, not to anger the world. Yet truly we ſee that this leſſon, as being en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grauen with the finger of God in their ſouls, doth remain deep he imprinted in all there wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> whereas <hi>Iames</hi> telleth vs; <hi>there is one lawgiuer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">I am. 4.12.</note> 
               <hi>which is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſaue &amp; diſtroy, who art thou that iudgeſt another man,</hi> that
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:13226:12"/>takeſt vppon thee to giue him a law (how great ſo euer thou art) that may binde his conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and giue or take from him life euerlaſting.<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 1.</note> And <hi>S. Iohn That which we haue ſeene and heard of that word of life, declare we vnto you.</hi> we haue learned it both for you and for our ſelfes; <hi>that you might haue felloſhip with vs &amp; that our fellowſhip might be with the father and with his ſon Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> This is the reward of hearing him. Farre different from that which once they aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, to witt, his right ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d or his left hand here on earth. <hi>S. Peter</hi> alſo alleadging for a reaſon this ſame viſion;<note place="margin">2. Pet. 1.8 16.17.</note> 
               <hi>For we followed not deceauable fables whenwe opened vnto you the comming and power of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, but with our eies we ſaw his Maieſtie, when there came ſuch a voice to him ſent fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that excellent glory,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:13226:12"/>This is my beloued ſonne &amp;c.</hi> &amp; then making a difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the doctrine of the law &amp; that of the Goſpell, between <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Elias,</hi> which he had ſeene, and that <hi>Ieſus</hi> whome he was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded to harken vnto: he goeth on thus, <hi>We haue the word of the prophets,</hi>
               <note place="margin">V. 9.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>to the which ye doe well that yee take heed.</hi> But as to what? <hi>as vnto a light, that ſhineth in a darke place.</hi> and how long? <hi>vntil the day dawne, and the day ſtarre ariſe in your harts.</hi> This Ieſus the Sonne of righteouſnes, the true light of our ſoules, of the which all the Propheſies are but litle ſparkes; this Ieſus, of whom Peter ſaid, when he had knowne him, <hi>To whom ſhould we goe? Lord, thou haſt the words of everlaſting life.</hi> Thou haſt them, that is to ſay, none hath them, but thou, but by thee: thou art the only head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:13226:13"/>ſpring of them; all others <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> but ſtinking ciſternes. In ſon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> other place perhaps wee might find the words of life, but of a temporall life,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> of a mortall life, of an immortall death. Wordes of ſaluation and happineſſe are not found but in Ieſus onely, in my Ieſus alone. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore with good reaſon was it told vs in the mountaine, <hi>Heare him.</hi> S. Paul was not at this viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and yet ſtickes not to taker the ſame leſſon for himſelf alſo,<note place="margin">Heb. 1. v. 1 &amp; 2.</note> 
               <hi>God</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>hauing at ſundry times and in divers maners spoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the old time to our fathers by the Prophets, in theſe laſt daies hath spoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto vs by his ſon.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. I 16.</note> In theſe laſt daies, ſaith hee, that is to ſay, for the laſt time, and for good reaſon, ſith that by this ſonne, <hi>the heire</hi> (as he addeth) <hi>of all things, by whom alſo hee made the worlds,</hi> that euerlaſting wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:13226:13"/>that aſſiſted him, <hi>when he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>epared the heavens,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 8. v. 27.</note> 
               <hi>when hee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et the compaſſe vpon the deepe.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eing deſcended neuertheleſſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ratiouſly from heauen, from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he boſome of the father, for to ſet vs aright in his waies. For which cauſe alſo he relateth not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nto vs theſe viſions and reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ations of his, which hee had ſeen,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 12.</note> 
               <hi>taken vp into the third hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, into Paradiſe, thoſe wordes which cannot be spoken.</hi> (What could not he haue told vs, if hee would but haue entertained the time with ſuch diſcourſes?) But thoſe things barely, which hee had learned of our Lord, for the ſaluation of the Churches, that is to ſay, of the aſſemb lies of the faithfull of all ſortes, men, women, children, learned, and vnlearned, vnto which hee did write;<note place="margin">1. Cor. 1 v. 23. &amp; 1 v. 3.</note> 
               <hi>I haue</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>receiued of the Lord that, which I haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:13226:14"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:13226:14"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:13226:15"/>vnto you; I haue delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto you that which I recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; the Goſpell whereby you are ſaved, if you keepe in memorie, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter what manner I preached it vnto you.</hi> If you keepe it ſtill the ſame, that I gaue it you, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out adding therevnto any thing of your owne. And the rather, becauſe <hi>I neither received it of man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 1. v. 12.</note> 
               <hi>nor was I taught it, but by revelation of Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> Is not that man therefore very arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant, that dares paſſe beyond that, within which theſe great Apoſtles doe keepe themſelues, &amp; bound both their preaching and writings? And after, yea &amp; beſides, this well beloued Son, this Sonne in whom the Father is well pleaſed, to teach and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound vnto vs, what the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of God is, and with what ſervice he is pleaſed; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon to adde ſomewhat of his
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:13226:15"/>owne minde, and diſplay his owne fancies and inuentions? Doth not this deſerue that God ſhould ſay vnto vs? Who hath required theſe thinges at your hands? Not to bee allowed, not to bee approued in your ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts? It is in vaine that you ſerue me to pleaſe men, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the inventions of men? He are him, whome I haue ſent you, him of whom I haue told you long ſince, that <hi>whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever will not harken vnto his words, I will require it of him.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 18. v. 19. &amp; 20</note> 
               <hi>For the Prophet that ſhall preſume to ſpeake a word in my name, which I haue not commaunded him to speake, even the ſame Prophet ſhall die,</hi> ſhal incurre everlaſting damnation. And here let theſe looke to themſelues, which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their own knowledge &amp; conſcience doe preach vnto the ſimple people ſo many things,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:13226:16"/>which they haue not heard fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, no nor from his Apoſtles; which are grounded only vpon viſions in the aire, vpon pretended reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, and certaine tales farre worſe then Apocryphall. Theſe notwithſtanding are articles of beleefe, more to be beleeued &amp; obſerved, nay more indeed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued and obſerued, then the worde of Chriſt and the holy Scriptures.</p>
            <p>But it may be that this is ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to thoſe three onely, thoſe three, which were taken apart by our Lord, &amp; were to learne ſome particular myſtery there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by. But that which is only ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to one of them (ſaith our Lord) is ſpoken vnto all. The myſteries and the ſecrets of God are not of the ſame nature that others are of; They are ſpoken in the eare, but to bee preached
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:13226:16"/>on the houſe tops. And indeed thou ſeeſt, that S. Paul did not ſticke to apply theſe wordes to himſelfe, and the fathers haue told thee that it concernes all the Apoſtles. And if all the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſties, then alſo all their diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and ſucceſſors, all ſuch as haue beleeued their word, and haue receiued from them their calling to teach the word, wee may ſay, all Chriſtians, all the faithfull, all the ſheepe of our great ſheepheard. <hi>For</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>my ſheep heare my voice,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 10.</note> 
               <hi>they vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand not the voice of a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, they flie backe from him.</hi> We may ſay, the very Catholike &amp; vniuerſall Church: For it is ſaid vnto her, <hi>Harken ô daughter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 45.10.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; conſider and incline thine eare.</hi> And how often hath it bin told vs, that that which is ſaid to Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, is ſaid to all his ſucceſſours, and to the whole Church? And
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:13226:17"/>for what reaſon ſhould it not hold herein alſo? To bee ſhort, when our Lord ſaith vnto his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, <hi>Hoc facite, do this,</hi> thou draweſt from thence a perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all inſtitution of a Sacrament, of a ſacrifice: when God therefore ſaith here ſolemnly, <hi>Hunc audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, Heare him;</hi> What right haſt thou to reſtrain it to theſe few, and to ſome peculiar myſtery, to the end that all thinges may be lawfull vnto you? With what face canſt thou deny, that theſe words doe containe a leſſon, which is to bee continuall and vniuerſall vnto the ende of the world, how to limit the faith and life of a Chriſtian within the compaſſe of Chriſt his voice, of Chriſt his lawe, of Chriſt his ſchoole, which is the only Lawgiuer, the only Maſter and only teacher in his Church?</p>
            <p>But there is more in it yet,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:13226:17"/>for this leſſon is more neceſſary for vs, then it was then for them or at any other time whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſince his Apoſtles. For vs, I ſay, on whome the laſt ages are come; for vs, whom ſo many a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, &amp; by a conſequent ſo many foreſtalled in their iudgement, haue preuented by anticipat o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, by inueterated cuſtoms, by preſidents of antiquitie, by renowne and maieſtie, which wil offer to part ſtakes with the Godhead. and make themſelues to be heard aboue the ſonne of God, aboue the Father himſelfe. For is there almoſt any age, that hath not brought forth its own teachers? Any teacher, that would not haue his priuat opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, his owne inuentions? I might ſay, hereſies. And is there any of them, that hath not built his own ſtubble on Chriſts fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, &amp; ſowne his owne tares
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:13226:18"/>in Chriſts field? And how may al this be remedied? Onely by this word alone, <hi>Heare him,</hi> heare none other; let euery o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther voice be ſuſpected by you. Vnto him that ſear cheth for the truth, doubteth of his way, and ſeeketh life; he, who is the truth, the way and the life, which alſo wil teach them, doth of his own accorde offer himſelfe. And where then ſhall wee ſeek him? This againe was an eaſie matter for his Apoſtles<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which had him at hand. which were dayly in his company, and did as it were draw it out of his breaſt. For S. Paul likewiſe, to whom it was yet graunted to heare him, though in lightning &amp; in thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. But whither ſendeſt thou vs to heare him? He which is aſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into heauen, and fitteth at the right ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of the Father, will not deſcend from thence, vntill
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:13226:18"/>he comes to iudge the worlde. And in the mean time what ſhal become of our doubtings? A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wait patiently; our Lord is not ſo farre from thee as thou ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gineſt. <hi>Say not in thy heart,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 10. v. 6 7. &amp; 8.</note> 
               <hi>who ſhall aſcend into heaven? That is to bring Chriſt from aboue. Or, who ſhall deſcend into the deepe? That is to bring Chriſt againe from the dead. The word is neere thee. This is the word of faith.</hi> The Goſpell which we read by the grace of our God, &amp; which we preach. Ieſus Chriſt hath not left vs Orphans. Hee hath not beene preuented by death, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing death in his owne power; He is not dead without making a Teſtament, nor gon from earth vp into heauen without a laſt will. By his Teſtament he ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth yet at this day, and did ſpeake in all the ages paſt, and giueth his law to his family. A
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:13226:19"/>Baſtard he is or vnthankful, that doth not heare him; It is his Goſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pell, and his holy Scriptures, in the which he liueth, and teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and iudgeth, and beareth rule in his Church. This Goſpel, by whoſe rule hee directeth the faithfull, correcteth and repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth the hereticks and vnbelee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, and putteth a difference between the one and the other; Of which S. Ireneus tels thee; <hi>That Gospell which the Apoſtles haue preached, haue they ſince gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and delivered vnto vs, tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derunt, in the Scriptures by the will of God, to bee the foundation of our faith.</hi> Then is it not by oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion only, or by their owne inſtinct, as ſome would make vs Beleeue,<note place="margin">Auguſt de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vang. l. 1.</note> S. Auguſtin; <hi>All that; which our Lord would that wee ſhould haue concerning his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s and his ſayings, he hath comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>to his Apoſtles to
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:13226:19"/>write it, as with his owne hands.</hi> As if therefore hee had writtten it himſelfe, if wee read it, wee heare himſelfe. And S. Cyrill ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth; <hi>All that,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cyril. l. 12 in loh c. 68.</note> 
               <hi>which they haue thought to ſuffice as well for man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners as for doctrine:</hi> Will we bee more able then they? S. Iohn al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the beloued Diſciple of our Lord;<note place="margin">Ioh. 20. v. 31.</note> 
               <hi>Theſe things are written</hi> not caſually, not by humane in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct, but <hi>that you might beleeue that Ieſus is that Chriſt that ſon of God, and that in beleeving yee might haue life through his name.</hi> And this beleeuing truely pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuppoſeth hearing, according to the wordes of the Apoſtle: Faith is by hearing, and hearing by the word of God. The Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell hath ſucceeded the law, but as the truth ſucceedeth the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, and manhood infancie, that the doctrin might be made cleane, and the condition of the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:13226:20"/>Church amended. God not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing content that his lawe had bin written with his owne fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, commaunded alſo that it ſhould bee written in a booke, that they ſhould look in it, that euery houſhold from their firſt yeares ſhould bee inſtructed in it. Truly Chriſt the ſon of God, our only lawgiuer, hath in like manner prouided for his Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell; being to leaue this world &amp; to withdraw his voice together with his fleſh from vs., hee hath perpetuated it vnto vs in his Goſpell. He hath giuen vs Eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſts &amp; Apoſtles, whoſe pens he hath inſpired. In them, &amp; by them, if thou wilt, hee ſpeaketh vnto thee, thou needeſt not climbe vp into a mountaine for it, or enter into a cloud, or be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertaken with feare; thou nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt only his bountifulneſſe and grace alone; of him, I ſay, ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:13226:20"/>in theſe Euangeliſts, his heauenly father telleth thee as well now as then; <hi>Heare him, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>are him in them.</hi> As well as our Lord at euery table where his Sacrament is celebrated ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his inſtitution, tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth thee yet throughout the whole world, <hi>Hoc facite. Doe this.</hi> And communicateth vnto thee on the one part his Spirit in his word, on the other his bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy, his fleſh, and his blood in his holy table. Which alſo is the reaſon, why every one of theſe good ancient fathers in al thoſe conflicts of hereſies did in times paſt betake themſelues to this teſtament, did therein take cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile from the mouth of Ieſus, as in old time fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God in the Arke and did therehence carie awaie healthfull anſwers to the peace of their conſcience, and the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cification of the Church. Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:13226:21"/>men, that we are, if ſome me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> had ſaid vnto vs, heare <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to,</hi> hearken vnto <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> wee would vnderſtand it ſo,<note place="margin">Opt S. Aug.</note> that he had directed vs to their books, and would goe to buy them at the Stationers: nor would wee any way trouble our ſelues to ſeeke their perſons either in Hell or in their feined Eliſian fieldes. But when it is ſaid vnto vs, <hi>Heare Chriſt,</hi> we begin to wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer make as if we were very idi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors, but indeed are malicious, &amp; aske where hee is? Herevpon marke what <hi>Optatus</hi> ſaith, that great African Doctour, conte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting againſt the Donatiſts.<note place="margin">Opt. Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>levit. l. 5. contra Parmen.</note> 
               <hi>You Donatiſts ſay, yea: we Catholiks ſay, Nay. In the midſt of your yea and our nay, mens ſoules are in doubt. None will beleeue you, nor. vs alſo; becauſe therefore that we are at ods, we muſt ſeeke iudges.</hi> The Chriſtians, ſaith he, are the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:13226:21"/>parties themſelues, the heathen cannot conceiue our myſteries. <hi>And therfore can there be found no iudgement on earth. Muſt wee ſeeke it in heaven?</hi> Note here the queſtion, &amp; marke how hee anſweres it. <hi>But what go wee to ſeeke for in heave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſeeing we haue a Teſtament in the Gospell? So long as the father is preſent, hee chargeth every one of his childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, what they are to do. There is as yet no need of any teſtament. And ſo Chriſt gaue to theſe Apoſtles their charge, whileſt yet he was on earth.</hi> But as an earthly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſeeing himſelfe to be neere the graue maketh his will, for to preuent and end all contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies betwixt his children; &amp; then men goe not to ſeeke him in his tombe, but in this will, wherein he ſpeaketh as if he li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and though dumbe yet is vnderſtood: <hi>ſo indeed,</hi> Chriſt,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:13226:22"/>
               <hi>he, that hath made the Teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, is in heaven, but let vs ſeeke his will in his Gospell, as in his teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. For even theſe very things, which ſome of you do now, hee did euen at that time ſee you do them.</hi> And as at that time he did fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee them, as being God euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, vnto whom all things are knowne from eternity, ſo with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt hee hath manifeſtlie prouided againſt them; he hath preuented all chances, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipated all tricks and cauils. heare alſo <hi>S. Auguſtin, Optatus</hi> his Country-man, which either had learned it of the other, or was inſpired by the ſame ſpirit. <hi>We are brethren, why ſtriue wee one with another? Our father di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not without a Teſtament; he made a will, and then died; died &amp; roſe againe. Men do pleade con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the ſucceſſion of the dead, vntill the will be brought forth; It
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:13226:22"/>being brought forth, every one is ſilent, that it may be opened &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſed. The Iudge harkeneth at tentiuely, the Advocates holde their peace, the Cryers cauſe ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, the people ſtands in ſuspe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſe, whileſt that the wordes of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed are a reading, who lyeth in his tomb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> without feeling, and yet his words haue their force. Chriſt is ſeated in heaven, &amp; ſhall he bee contradicted in his Teſtament?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſt. in Pſal. 21.</note> 
               <hi>Open then, and let vs read<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> we are brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, why are we at variance? Let vs appeaſe our anger: our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath not left vs without a Teſtament.</hi> His Goſpels; A Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament. ſaith <hi>S. Baſill,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Baſil. de Fide.</note> vnto which nothing ought to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. It would be falſe; nay ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. <hi>The Apoſtle,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>by a worldly example forbiddeth vs expreſtie to adde any thing to the holy Scripture, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſaith; And notwithſtanding no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reiecteth
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:13226:23"/>the Teſtament of a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or addeth any thing therevnto, if it hath once beene eſtabliſhed. Wherefore we haue alwaies knowne, that we muſt flie from every voice and all meanings, which are beſide the doctrin of our Lord.</hi> Beſide, ſaith he, and not <hi>againſt.</hi> And now in the mouth of theſe three wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, ſhall not our ſpeech be confirmed vnto you? God will haue it, &amp; hath appointed that his well beloued Son ſhould be heard. Heard here beneath, ſo long as he conuerſed here in his owne perſon: and heard in his holy Goſpell, ſealed vnto vs by his Apoſtles by the will of the Father, and the comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dement of the Sonne, ſince that he hath been lifted vp from this world.</p>
            <p>Heard, doe you tell vs, in his Goſpell? I &amp; you to heare him. Then behoveth it vs to reade. May we do ſo, without being
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:13226:23"/>excommunicated or anathema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed? A book ſo dangerous, full of ambuſhes, full of ſnares? HOW the world is changed, nay euen the very voice of the Church ſince the time of theſe good fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers? That the law of our Lord, which is to decide all our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſies ſhould be eſteemed of in theſe daies as a matter of que<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtion; and this Teſtament which ought to bring to an agreeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t the moſt contentious brethren, as a bundle of contradictorie clauſes. Could this Teſtament euer haue beene altered? Seeing that we agree in this, that it could not, what remaines then, but that this alteration pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds not from the truth of the thing, but from the malice of the perſons? Thy father hath made a wil: doth it not concern thee to ſee what hee leaueth thee; and vnder what title; to
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:13226:24"/>know alſo what things he char<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geth thee to doe? Were hee the greateſt ſtranger in the world, wouldſt thou not be ſo curious as to reade it? Hee that would conceale it from thee, yea and keepe thee from reading it, couldſt thou beleeue he did this without fraud? And being curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in euery other thing, wilt thou be negligent in this? Thou that ſeemſt to bee a quicke fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, and wouldſt bee eſteemed of for ſuch a one in all thy buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; wilt thou in this bee an i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diot, &amp; leſſe then a babe? Canſt thou doe this without a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt to God? Canſt thou doe this if Goſpell, and an eternall life? Tell mee in thy conſcience, if thou hadſt lived in the time that our Lord converſed here in his fleſh, and hadſt had the grace to acknowledge him to bee that
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:13226:24"/>Chriſt that Sonne of the living God; wouldſt thou haue made any difficultie, or thought it to be any grievous fault, or an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecrable deede to heare him preach? Wouldſt thou not on the contrary, haue gon to ſeeke after this divine worde, euen in the midſt of the wilderneſſe (Whatſoever the Scribes and the Phariſes had ſaid vnto thee) wouldſt not thou haue had thine attentiue care linked to his ſacred mouth? And behold, when he was to aſcend vp into heaven, for to lift you vp thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther after him, hee hath ſealed the ſame vnto you in his Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, in his Goſpels, which for the greater part are nothing but his Sermons; his ſpeeches ſet downe by writing, that thou maiſt read them and read them againe more diſtinctly &amp; more cleerely, chew and chew them
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:13226:25"/>againe at your eaſe; written ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly by ſundry Evangeliſts, that for thine inſtruction the one may giue light &amp; ſerue for an interpreter to the other. And yet ſhall men make you beleeue that the pen and ſtile of his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangeliſts and Apoſtles, though ledde by the ſame Spirit, by that Spirit, which was promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vnto them, was <hi>to bring in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their memory all that which he had told them,</hi> hath connected this ſauing, <hi>this quickning word,</hi> into a dead letter, a murthering and condemning letter; that thou mighteſt abhor it, and flie from it, and caſt it into the fire, I &amp; thy ſelfe becauſe of it? why then what needed this worde haue bin giuen vnto vs in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>by the will of God,</hi> as <hi>S. Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neus</hi> told vs before, and <hi>by the commandement of Chriſt,</hi> as <hi>S. Auguſtin</hi> repeated it, but that
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:13226:25"/>it might be reade? And why ſhould it be read leſſe, then the law and the Prophets, by al be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuers. <hi>S. Peter</hi> called Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſying a candle, but the Goſpel a Sun, a full midday, ſuch a lighte as can admit no increaſe. True<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly our Sauiour wrought mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles enough, in the which his diuinity appeared both effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally and euidently; And for all this yet ſendeth he the Iewes to the law &amp; the Prophets. <hi>Search</hi> ſaith he, <hi>the Scriptures.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 5.</note> And we finde not that they reply vnto him: we are forbidden them. <hi>S. Paul</hi> alſo exerciſing his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtleſhip among the Iewes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth into a Synagogue of the citie of <hi>Berea;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 17.</note> &amp; as he was pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfull in the holy ſcriptures, hee preached vnto them that Ieſus is the Chriſt. What doe then thoſe of <hi>Berea?</hi> They were not ignoraunt of that ſo notorious
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:13226:26"/>viſion which <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſaw in the way to <hi>Damaſcus,</hi> they might likewiſe haue laid a foundation on ſuch ſignes and miracles, as confirmed his ſayings. And ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſſe the Euangeliſt <hi>Saint Luke</hi> telleth vs, that <hi>they recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the word with all readineſſe,</hi> but by what meanes? <hi>Searching the Scriptures daily, whether thoſe things were ſo:</hi> to wit, as <hi>S. Paul</hi> had preached vnto them. And this is the reaſon, why <hi>S. Luke</hi> telleth vs, that they were <hi>more noble men then thoſe, which were at Theſſalonica:</hi> by this liue lie faith, which they with a zeal mixed with knoweledge, did draw out of the reading of the holy Scriptures. Whence alſo it is that hee addeth that <hi>many of them beleeved, and of honourable wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which were Grecians.</hi> Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men therfore at that time were not reproued, but commended
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:13226:26"/>by the Euangeliſt, by the holie Ghoſt himſelf, for hauing read, conferred, and ſearched the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures; And that alſo, that they might iudge of the doctrin and preaching of <hi>S. Paul</hi> that excellent Apoſtle. Now what is it that the Goſpell coulde ſince haue done vnto vs, what euill hath it done to Chriſtendome, that we ſhould feare or abhorre the reading thereof? Truly whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as <hi>S. Iohn</hi> telleth vs, <hi>theſe things are writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ye might beleeue:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 20. v. 31.</note> He telleth vs co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſequently, that they are written, that yee might read them, and read them for to beleeue them, and therfore they may be vnderſtoode of vs, they are not ambiguous, they are fit of themſelues to perſwade vs, and to make vs beleeue. When<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as alſo <hi>S. Paule</hi> directed his Epi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtles, to the churches of Rome, of Corinth, of Galatia, of Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:13226:27"/>of Philippi, &amp;c? which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted of al ages, ſexes, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions; his purpoſe was not to exclude any one from them, he hath admitted al of vs thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to: vnto thoſe Epiſtles notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, in the which hee trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth moſt deeplie and profound<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly of the deepeſt and profoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt articles of the Chriſtian faith; and none of vs wil wrong him ſo far as to thinke, that his intent was thereby to deſtroie them, he being ſo powerful and ſo zealous in their inſtruction. The like is alſo to bee thought of <hi>S. Peter,</hi> and <hi>S. Iames,</hi> &amp; the other Apoſtles. But ſpeake wee alſo of the church in theſe pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitiue times. Of what folly doe we accuſe her, which tooke ſo great a care, to cauſe the newe teſtament to be tranſlated into all languages, that all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> might be able to vnderſtand it? Into
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:13226:27"/>the Latine, the Syrian, the Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bian, the Egyptian, the Ethio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pian, the Perſian, the Indian, the Scythian, the Sauromaticke, &amp; the Gothes language. And for what manner of men ſhall wee take S. Hierome, and S. Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome, which turned it into the Sclavonian and Armenian tongues, commending ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly the reading thereof vnto all perſons?<note place="margin">Chryſoſt. Hom. 3. de Lazaro. In Ioh. Hom 29. De verbo Eſay Hom 2. In opere Imperf. Homil 42 In Matt. Hom. 2. In Ioh. Homil. 16 In Geneſ. Hom. 12.13.21.</note> The one of them ſo farre as to ſay, that they are the inſtruments of every Chriſtian mans trade, that hee ought, and can no leſſe want them, then an artificer the implements of his ſhop, that he muſt ſpare no coſt for to buy them, that hee ought to haue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alwaies in his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, and not referre himſelfe either to Monke or Clergie man; but on the contrary hee ought to preiudice and iudge the ſermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the Preachers, I and his own
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:13226:28"/>too,<note place="margin">Ad Col. Hom 9 &amp; ad Theſſ. Hom. 3.</note> by reading before hand the ſame place, which is expounded vnto them: ought alſo to arme himſelfe againſt the Arrians, &amp; all other hereticks, becauſe it ſhall ſo happen (ſaith he, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peats it at ſundry times) that then when Antichriſt ſhall bee come with his army of hereſies, there ſhall bee left no other meanes to knowe the truth or true Chriſtianitie by, but <hi>onely,</hi> tantummodò,<note place="margin">Chryſoſt. in Opere Imperf. Hom 9</note> 
               <hi>by the Scriptures:</hi> No more at all by viſions, nor by miracles. The reader may find on that ſame ſubiect many homilies, in the which hee can never bee cloid, almoſt whole ones together, which wee need not bring in here. <hi>Origen, S. Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſil, S. Ambroſe, S. Auguſtine, S. Hierom,</hi> ſay euery one the ſame alſo. When as the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> men ſpake of of the Scriptures quite other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe at this day; and vſe as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:13226:28"/>inhibitions for to remoue vs from them, as theſe good Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers had exhortations for to bring vs neere them: when as men tell vs, as vnto little chril<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, take heed therof, the wolfe is there: can we heare this, and not haue cauſe to ſuſpect them? And what then is more likely, then to beleeue rather that our Church is much changed, ſith that the voice of our teachers is quite different from that of theſe holy Fathers: &amp; that they ſet our candleſticke vnder a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſhel, for feare we ſhould per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue theſe deformities &amp; gaps, or ſeeke after a reformation, or call them into the law, at leaſt to repentance?</p>
            <p>Therefore, <hi>Hunc audite,</hi> Heare Ieſus our ſaviour, heare him in his Scriptures. But to make vſe of them: Heare him with due reverence: Think with
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:13226:29"/>your ſelfe, when you alight vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this newe Teſtament of our Lord, that you enter into the temple of God, into his ſanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arie; that Chriſt preacheth vnto vs therein, that it is his voice, which is the truth and the way: that it is not for naught, that the Church hath called theſe Scriptures Canonicall, <hi>that is to ſay Regular,</hi> they being rules di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting our faith and our ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nter therefore with invo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of Gods holy name, by the ſame Ieſus, requiring of him his holy Spirit, that may inſpire you, enlighten you, &amp; gine you an acceſſe to his myſteries: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing void of all paſſions, &amp; full of holy affections, hungring af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſalvation, and covetous of his glory. And doubt not, but that ſeeking him there, for there he is, he wil be found of thee; &amp; knacking at this dore he will o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:13226:29"/>vnto thee, hee will preuent thee, and draw thee vnto hinn The Eunuch of the Queene of the Ethiopians,<note place="margin">Act. 8.</note> read <hi>Eſaias</hi> the Prophet in his chariot; read him but vnderſtood him not. And yet found he there Ieſus, whom he ſcarſe ſought after; <hi>Philip</hi> ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning vnto him, being carried by the Spirit, for to bee his truche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, his interpreter. Thus is God at hand to thoſe that ſeek his Son in the Scriptures. Thus alſo is the Son himſelfe deligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in being ſought after here, and in offering himſelfe to bee fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d here in his ſchoole. Which being riſen and glorified, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to his diſciples at Emma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, when he might haue ſhewne them his wounds, tokens of his mortality and alſo of his God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, had rather reſolue them in their doubts by <hi>Moſes</hi> &amp; by the Prophets. <hi>Did not our harts,</hi>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:13226:30"/>ſaid they, <hi>burne within vs, while he talked with vs by the way, and whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he opened vnto vs the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</hi> Why then ſimple people &amp; idiots as we are, you will ſay, (for I ſpeak euen vnto them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo) in theſe Scriptures what are we to do? Thou Chriſtian, that haſt thy conſcience doubtful a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the controverſies of this time: thou ſhalt conſult with <hi>Ieſus</hi> thy Sauiour in this his word on them. In a matter of great doubt thou co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſulteſt with thine Advocate, &amp; wilt beleeue his writings therin. What wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g then ſhalt thou do to thy Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, in a matter of thine owne ſaluation, if thou wilt not heare him, if thou wilt not beleeue him? Thou ſhalt alſo in reading it ſee before thee the chiefe points of thy Religion, wherof thou art in doubt; Thoſe, that aboue others are commaunded
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:13226:30"/>and commended vnto you; of which ether the beliefe is more ſtrictly preſcribed vnto thee, or the practiſe in ſpecial vrged vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thee: for to obſerue or not to obſerue thoſe, which are told thee to procure greater ſinne or greater reward. Thou ſhalt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue in theſe holy Scriptures the words of thy Sauiour, &amp; the rules of thy ſaluation; if there be any mention made of them, and in what manner, if in the ſame manner, as men teach them vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, as they are celebrated in thy church, though not in name, yet at leaſt in effect, though not in expreſſe tearmes, yet at leaſt in ſuch as are equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. In briefe, if in the reading of theſe holy Scriptures thou canſt finde out the beliefe, the doctrine, the diſcipline, the face the viſage, and lineamentes of thine owne church<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and of that,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:13226:31"/>which is taught, beleeued, and done in thy church. Truely if thou canſt perceiue all this, call then thy ſelfe happy, think that thou art in Paradiſe, where the voice of <hi>Ieſus,</hi> where his worde is heard. From this church be thou neuer deſirous to departe. But ſay with the Apoſtle, <hi>who ſhal ſeparate me</hi> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this church, wherin is felt <hi>the loue of Chriſt? Shall tribulation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8 35</note> 
               <hi>or anguiſh, or perſecution, or famine, or naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, or perill, or ſworde? No, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther death, nor life, nor Angels, nor principalities, nor powers.</hi> For what greater conſolation can there be in this conflict of opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, then to haue peace in his conſcience; and in theſe ſo dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous occurrents, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured of his way? Of the true faith warranted by the word of his God, and, by a conſequent, of his ſaluation? But on the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:13226:31"/>if thou findeſt nothing therein of the moſt part of that which men preach vnto thee, &amp; make thee beleeue, and inioine thee to do; if in the inward and in the outward, in the doctrine &amp; in the diſcipline, thou findeſt altogither a different voice and different hue; haſt not thou the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cauſe to doubte, that thou art ſtraied from the Sheepefolde of thy Sauiour, where thou knew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt not his voice, but the voice rather of a ſtranger, in words &amp; doctrines ſo ſtrange, that it is now no longer the true temple of God, ſeeing that it is an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then our Sauiour, that cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth his voice there to ſound, &amp; hath ſeaſed on the chaire there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of? And what remaineth then, but that with the ſpouſe in the Canticles thou ſayeſt vnto him, <hi>Shew me ô thou whom my ſoule lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cant 1.6<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> 
               <hi>where thou feedeſt, where
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:13226:32"/>thou lyeſt at noone: for why ſhould I bee as ſhee that turneth aſide?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 25. &amp; 23.</note> 
               <hi>Shew me thy waies, ô Lord, direct me in thy truth, ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d me thy light, let it lead me, let is bring me into thy Tabernacles.</hi> Tabernacles in deed in regarde of that ſtatelie building of this temple, wherin I finde my ſelfe to bee, and of a ſmall ſhew, and very contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible. But be they what they wil yet are they the tabernacles &amp; boothes of that chiefe. Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard, which I ſeeke for, whoſe skins and cords hee will ſtretch out when it ſhall pleaſe him; &amp; in the meane time I ſhal be ſure to finde there my Shepheard, <hi>I ſhall not want.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 23.</note> That good Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearde, which <hi>laieth downe his life for his ſheepe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 10.</note> and lifteth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all vp euen <hi>the little lambes, into his boſome;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſa. 40.11</note> doth waſh them in the poole of Siloa, feedeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the hand, and nouriſheth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:13226:32"/>vp with himſelfe into life ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting. Whereas in this fained Temple I was fed with nothing but ſmoake, with winde, with ſound, with pride, with rumour with luxury; I laide out, as the Prophet ſaith, my ſiluer and my labour for that which neither did nouriſh nor ſatisfie:<note place="margin">Eſay. 55.</note> in idle ſuffrages, in vaine ſeruices, and erroneous indeed becauſe vain.</p>
            <p>Here againe is another ſtop. What then? The Religion of Chriſt, the true one, the only re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ligion, doth ſhe not admit of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny increaſe or change? May not men adde therunto ſome Laws, ſome articles, ſome new cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies? Learne this my friend, that the true religion, as a man from his firſt birth, hath all his members, all his ioints, any the leaſt part cannot be taken from it; (thou findeſt it ſo in thine owne body,) without maiming
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:13226:33"/>it; any the nobleſt, that thou canſt imagine, cannot be appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vnto it out of the work, with out diſproportion, without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity, without wronging the whole frame: if any thing be in it more then ſhould be, it is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuberancie, or ſome vnnaturall fleſh that groweth out; becauſe that Religion is not a thing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented by man, but by a diuine Law, and the rule of Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and of mans ſaluation; and none other but God can giue or enioine it vnto man; becauſe that his thoughts are aboue the thoughts of man, and are high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er then the heauens that are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the earth;<note place="margin">Cor. 2.1.</note> becauſe that no man knoweth the thinges of a man ſaue the ſpirit of a man; not one man of another ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, though they haue the ſame ofspring, &amp; do conſiſt of the ſame faculties and like parts; but every one of
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:13226:33"/>himſelfe. And with much more reaſon then; <hi>no man hath known,</hi> no man hath ever beene able to know, <hi>the things of God but the spirit of God. Who art thou,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſa. 40 13</note> ſaith the Prophet, <hi>that inſtructeſt the spirit of the Lord; or art his cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſailour to teach him any thing?</hi> And hence it is that we ſee, all thoſe authours of religions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the heathen, to haue bin ſo childiſh and ridiculous in their ceremonies; and can we i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magine, that, when wee vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take to adde any thing to that religion, which was ordeined from God by Ieſus Chriſt, wee ſhould be leſſ ſo the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they were? can we thinke, that the dirt and duſt, and ſmoke, which we caſt vpon it, can any way honor, nay canne it chuſe but disfigure or pollute his worke? And neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe, do not thou think ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that the Doctours in the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:13226:34"/>church are vnprofitable, or that they are not very profitable, that the church &amp; her members all and euery one of them can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not helpe or grow vp. Truely the right Religion can growe both in it ſelfe and in thee, hath growne heretofore, and can al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies goe on in grouth. But learne alſo how ſhee groweth. She groweth in her ſelfe, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in thee alſo, (if thou canſt make thine vſe of it,) when the old Teſtament hath taught thee that it behooved the Chriſt of God to die and riſe againe; and the new, that hee hath died in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, and is riſen againe. And beholde a ſufficient clowde of witneſſes, of holy martyrs, which many ages ago, by hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds and thouſandes togither haue died for the witnes of this death, of this reſurrection; &amp; by their ſuffrings and deaths haue
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:13226:34"/>ſubdued the world vnto him, &amp; knit together vnder the banner of his croſſe thoſe which hee hath ſeparated from the world: doſt not thou thinke that theſe articles, <hi>I beleeue that he roſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine from the dead; I beleeue the reſurrection of the body,</hi> are very well perfected by them, well growne, and ſtrengthned both in them and in thee, ſo far as to beleeue them, and to embrace them euen to the death for this faith, ſeeing that by this faith thou art to liue? Behold alſo, the lawe hath told thee, that this Chriſt ſhould be the ſon of God and neuertheleſſe be borne of a Virgin: and the Goſpell, that he is that Ieſus that ſonne of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God, God of God, &amp; there fore from everlaſting as the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and that word nevertheles made fleſh, conceiued in the wombe of the Virgin Mary;
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:13226:35"/>God and man, both together. Sundry heretickes, Arius and Neſtorius aboue the reſt, begin they to call in queſtion ſome his eternity and Godhead, and ſome his manhood and morta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, and by a conſequent the Character of the Saviour of the world; wherevpon the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie through his ſpirit ſtirreth vp many great doctors fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, powerful in the Scriptures, which by the ſame doe ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come and convince them, doe demonſtrate with efficacie in one only perſon as well the one as the other nature; both the wills as well the one as the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be neceſſarie for our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; the one working with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out preiudice to the other. And that by places well expounded and aſwell applied, and by ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments drawne from them, both ſtrong in themſelues and,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:13226:35"/>as ſtrongly vrged; ſo that after many cumbats the field is left to the truth, the victory &amp; glory to the ſimplicitie, and to that ſeeming weakneſſe of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell. Doſt not thou thinke that theſe articles of our creed, <hi>I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue in Ieſus Chriſt the only ſon of the Father Almightie our Lord,</hi> borne of the virgin Mary, conceiued by the holy Ghoſt; theſe very ſame in number, as they vſe to ſpeak in the ſchools, haue bred in thee a new impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; in themſelues new forces? The like alſo is to bee thought of ſo many others, for all that the hereticks doe ſet vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which harden and make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues ſtrong againſt them; and we by them, as wreſtlers againſt the skirmiſh, according as the hereticks do trouble &amp; vex the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Thoſe articles of the fall of man by himſelf, of his reſtitution by
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:13226:36"/>one Ieſus alone; of the grace of God, of free iuſtification, for all that <hi>Pelagius, Celeſtius,</hi> &amp; their conſorts, either lay battery a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them or vndermine the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: ſtand faſt notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, with out once moving the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, where the Maſter-builder placed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, make no breach in the propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the building, &amp; ſtir not from their firſt conformity, to the which nothing ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be added, but in the manner of a botch, quite contrary to the nature of the firſt Law giuers intent, and to that Lawe, in the which no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can bee altered without high treaſon, &amp; from which no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be derogated without ſacriledge.<note place="margin">Vincent. Lirinen. contra hęreti cos</note> Heare therevpon, what ſaith our <hi>Vincentius Liri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenſis;</hi> (for in ſuch matters I ſpeake not willingly without mine authour; and ſuch an au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour as may pleaſe thee.) <hi>The
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:13226:36"/>Canon,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>of the Scriptures is perfect, and more then ſufficient in it ſelfe for al things.</hi> What the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall it not bee lawfull to put ſomewhat of our own there vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to? <hi>Timothy,</hi> ſaith hee, <hi>thou that art a Doctour of the Church,</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitum cuſtodi, <hi>keep that which hath beene truſted vnto thee, thou haſt received it of gold, giue it vp againe of gold, I will haue no lead nor braſſ or baſe mettle from you: God hath hee endowed thee with his spirit, or with learning, then be thou a Bezeleel in his spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Tabernacle,</hi> in his church, <hi>cut and ſquare theſe pretious ſtones of his divine doctrine, ſet them cunningly in ſome worke, giue a luſter vnto them, and a ſparkling, and grace.</hi> But goe no farther then hee did, preſume not to change any thing either in the matter or the forme, which the Lord hath preſcribed vnto thee:
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:13226:37"/>vnto this Bezeleel God had preſcribed of euery thing, euen to the very badgers skins, and the loopes of the Tabernacle, he had left him nothing to doe after his owne minde. For what ſerues then both his and our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrie? <hi>That by thee,</hi> ſaith hee, <hi>men may vnderſtand that more cleerely, which before they belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved more obſcurely.</hi> One and the ſame article of faith, more cleer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, but no newe one, none of thine owne head. <hi>That in tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching that, which thou haſt lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, thou maiſt ſay the ſame things after a new manner,</hi> with a new grace or methode, <hi>but no new things;</hi> nothing, that is not in this rule of holy Scripture; <hi>nove</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>non nova.</hi> And he addeth, that this is not ſaid vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Timothie in particular, <hi>but to the whole Church, to the whole body of thoſe that haue any
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:13226:37"/>charge therein,</hi> becauſe that this <hi>Depoſitum, is a thing which hath beene commanded thee, and thou thy ſelfe haſt not invented; which thou haſt receiued, and thou thy ſelfe haſt or forged. It is no worke of chine owne wit, but it was taught thee; it is no matter of private vſurpation, but of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique graunt.</hi> In reſpect of which laſtly, <hi>thou oughteſt not be the author, but the keeper, not the ordainer, but the follower; thou oughteſt not to lead others, but to follow.</hi> And to ſpeake truely, what neede is there of all theſe inventions, and of ſo many careeres, as we giue, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnprofitable to our owne wittes, for to beautifie the Religion, to our owne fanſie? <hi>As if,</hi> ſaith hee, <hi>it were not an heavenly doctrine, and ſuffiſed to haue beene once revealed; but an earthly inſtitution, and
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:13226:38"/>could never be perfected but by a continual amendme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t,</hi> according as men vſe to deliberate toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of one thing to day, and to morrow of another. After him, which flouriſhed about ſome twelue hundred yeares agoe, all wearied and tired by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentions of his own time, what is there that wee may not now ſay? Shall we eſteeme of it as he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie, or a luſt after ſchiſme, to call the Church backe againe vnto Chriſt, vnto his holy word and vnto his holy Scriptures? Therefore, <hi>Hunc audite, Heare Ieſus,</hi> heare him, yee which haue heard ſo many others, and that to your great harme; heare him, and ſhut your care vnto them, which was too open to humane teachings, and is from hence forth to bee reſerued for his voice alone. But becauſe that our cares are vncircumciſed, &amp;
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:13226:38"/>filled with fatte, let vs beſeech this everlaſting Sonne, that by his ſpirit he would cleanſe them and pearce them even vnto our hearts, and vnto our ſoules, for to heare and vnderſtand our Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, and his voice, in his word, and in his doctrine, and that he will graunt, that wee may heare it, to beleeue it with our hearts; that we may beleeue it, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe it to ſaluation; and that we may profeſſe it to the edificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our neighbours and his Church. But aboue all, becauſe that in his language to heare is to obey, and that truely to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue and to doe well, doe na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally follow the one vpon the other: let vs make our ſupplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion vnto him, that he will giue vs the grace, to be of the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of thoſe, which harken vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his word and keep it; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing conſequently built, &amp; lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:13226:39"/>our foundation on that Rocke, which all the waues of the ſea can neuer ſhake, and the gates of hell with all their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavors can never approach vn to; we may then be aſſured, that as he hath graunted vs here be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath to bee of the number of his true diſciples, ſo hee will make vs in heauen aboue, (not vpon this earthly mountaine) partakers of his full glory; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that there we cannot ſay, as S. Peter did, <hi>Let vs make here three Tabernacles,</hi> as being ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſhed with the ſenſe of a light ſhadow of this heauenly glorie; but rather as being both better in our wits, and better inſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and that by himſelfe, wee are to heare him, and to depend on his ſayings, and to ſeeke him in his word, wherein hee makes vs to vnderſtand him, as being the finiſher of the law, and the
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:13226:39"/>author of ſaluation in his Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, yea himſelfe being that ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation; that ſo, when the earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly habitation of this our abode ſhall come to be deſtroyed, wee may be carried vp into that buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and euerlaſting houſe, which was neuer made with hands, but hath beene prepared by the father for his Diſciples. Now to him be all honour and glorie with the Sonne and the holy Ghoſt for euer and euer.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="homily">
            <pb n="72" facs="tcp:13226:40"/>
            <head>NON SIC FVIT ab initio. MATTH. 19. v. 8.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E haue told you that two onely words out of the Goſpell were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to decide the moſt parte of doubts, that are at this day in Chriſtendome; and wee haue already expounded vnto you one of them, <hi>Hunc audite, Hear him,</hi> that well beloued Sonne, that Sonne and Chriſt of God, in his worde, in his holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. Whereby are cutte off all forged articles of faith or of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, that haue no foundation
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:13226:40"/>all in this his worde. Now fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth the ſecond; <hi>Non ſic fuit ab initio: From the beginning it was not ſo.</hi> Which baniſheth out of the Church, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly blotteth out in our conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, whatſoeuer the inuention or imitation of man, either in imitation of the Iewes and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans, or in loue of their owne fanſies, hath added to thoſe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry articles, which are grounded in the holy Scriptures, in ſo much, that wee haue need from time to time to recall them to their firſt inſtitution, &amp; begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, it belonging to the ſame diuinitie, and being of the ſame kind, nature, and conſequence, to inuent new articles of faith, or to caſt the old ones anew, to inſtitute a religion in the whol, or in ſome parts. Ieſus Chriſt therefore being asked by the Phariſes, which came to tempt
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:13226:41"/>him, whether it be lawfull for a man to put away his wife, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers them by the law of God; <hi>Haue yee not read that hee which made the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at the beginning, made them male and female; and would haue them twaine to be one fleſh?</hi> And let no man therefore put aſunder that, which God hath coupled together. Here was wherewithall to ſtoppe their mouth. But they neuertheleſſe reply; <hi>Why then did Moſes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund to giue a bill of divorce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</hi> This proud nation oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Moſes to God, the ſeruant to the maſter, the creature to his Creator. But what anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth our Sauiour, which was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen meekneſſe and humblenes it ſelfe, but yet for all that aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted nothing from the glory of the father? <hi>Moſes becauſe of the hardneſſe of your heart hath ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered you to doe ſo.</hi> A number of
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:13226:41"/>things haue either bin brought in or tolerated in the Church vnder this pretenſe; <hi>But from the beginning it was not ſo;</hi> Such was not the inſtitution of mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage ordained by God, that great lawgiuer; to this original it is that he calleth them, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any reſpect of their preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptions. <hi>I ſay therefore vnto you,</hi> I which was preſent with God, being coeternall with him, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he made them, when hee cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled them together, when hee bleſſed them, which knowe his meaning, and the reaſon of the law, which alſo will cauſe it to be followed, <hi>Whoſoever ſhall put away his wife, except it bee for whoredome, and marrie another, committeth adulterie.</hi> How ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thinges might the Phariſes haue to ſay hereupon, in a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter wherein Moſes was tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, that great captaine of
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:13226:42"/>Gods people, which had ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to him face to face, had receiued the law from his hand, authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by ſo many miracles? By a preſcription of two thouſand yeares? By ſo long a forbeara<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce? And that vnder ſo many kings, Prieſts, and Prophets? And yet they ſtand here at a ſtay, &amp; yeeld without once co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tradicting this ſentence; <hi>From the beginning it was not ſo;</hi> In Paradiſe this was ordered otherwiſe. If then this hold in a law that concernes on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ciuill ſocietie, howe much more in Eccleſiaſticall lawes, which concerne religion, and Gods ſervice? the articles of our faith, the ſaluation of our ſouls, and things ſpirituall? Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the naturall man diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth nothing, nor the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall man perceiueth an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e more, then as far as the Spirit of God guideth him, and being
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:13226:42"/>guided by the ſpirit of God ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> go no farther, then as he keepes himſelfe to his word; how illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated ſoeuer he either bee or ſeeme to be, he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> adde nothing to Gods work, to his comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement; whatſoeuer he putteth to it, is but imperfect and full of filth. And hence it is that the Politicians do ſo often rehearſe vnto vs, that to the vpholding of the lawes of any common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, it is neceſſarie that they ſhould be recalled from time to time to their principles; to wit, againſt all tricks, &amp; ſide-ſtroaks as it were of ſuch as wreſt &amp; de praue them. And therefore for a greater cauſe was Gods people enioind ſo carefully to knowe the law of God and his ſeruice at their fingers end; that ſo, as many men as there were of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſo many co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trollers there might be in the church, for to keep hir
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:13226:43"/>in and call her backe againe to her bounds. And therefore was it that <hi>Eſay</hi> cryed ſo lowd: <hi>To the Law and to the Teſtimony,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay. 8.20</note> 
               <hi>if they speake not according to this word, it is becauſe ther is no light in them.</hi> No ſaluation for this people. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is this a rule, which is to be receiued for the directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Gods church, &amp; to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine all whatſoeuer concernes the true religion, the whole du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of man towards God, &amp; his owne ſaluation: and for ſuch a one hath it indeede alwaies bin vſed, as often as there was in hande any reformation of the Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>David</hi> had eſtabliſhed Gods ſeruice, in the middeſt of his people, according to the ten or of his law. And many of his ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, either dronken with the ſeruice of falſe Gods, or neglecting the ſeruice of the
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:13226:43"/>true God, had partly corrupted it, and partly ſuffered it to go to decay; and now that good king <hi>Ioſaphat,</hi> mooued with a true zeal of God, is about to reſtore it againe: It is ſaid,<note place="margin">2. Chron. 17 v. 3. vn to the 9.</note> 
               <hi>That he wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked in the firſt waies of his father David.</hi> He ſtood not vpon that, which his father <hi>Aſa,</hi> though a godly Prince, had either done or tolerated, and ſtood as little alſo on that, which ſo many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in all this while had done, for to drawe a preſident from their example: but turned back euen vnto <hi>David,</hi> vnto <hi>the firſt waies</hi> of <hi>David,</hi> vnto his beſt yeares; and thoſe very beſt ones yet did he examine by the lawe of God: when it is added, that <hi>he ſought the</hi> God of his father; not that which his father had done, but that which the God of his father had appointed to he done; he walked in his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:13226:44"/>and not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that which Iſrael had done; he ordered himſelfe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the law, and not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the vſuall cuſtome of the church, <hi>he tooke away the high places and the groues out of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da,</hi> which had bin tolerated a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them by moſt of their beſt kings. To a young and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der king this toleration might haue ſcrued for an excuſe. And that his people might alſo ſeeke the ſame waies, he ſent Prieſtes and Leuites, as alſo ſome of the chiefe men of his Eſtate to aſſiſt them, <hi>That they ſhould teach thoſe of Iuda,</hi> But how? <hi>Having the booke of the law of the Lorde with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> for to recall their faith to this beleefe, their worſhip to his ordinances, their crooked &amp; depraued waies, to this ſquare, to this rule. And we find not, that in all this circuite, which
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:13226:44"/>they make, any one doth once obiect vnto them either the tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition or the authority of the church, or the toleration of the Fathers. So well had every one of them learned &amp; remembred, euen in the middeſt of that cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption; that there, where the God of their fathers ſpake, was no place at all to hearken vnto either the Church of Iſrael, or all their fathers togither.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe <hi>Hezekiah</hi> when he came to the crowne; he had had to his father king <hi>Ahaz,</hi> which had broken the veſſels of Gods houſe, and ſhut vp his temple; that is to ſay, had caſt down his ſeruice,<note place="margin">2 Chron. 28. v. 24.</note> &amp; built vp altars to the falſe Gods in all the citties of <hi>Iuda;</hi> inſteed of the true Altar, many thouſands of falſe ones, as ſuperſtition of its owne nature doth multiply; all this might haue beene a great ſtumbling
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:13226:45"/>blocke to this you<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g Prince, but yet he goeth on farther. Euen in the firſt yeare of his raigne, hee openeth the dores and repaires them; and which is more, doeth ſend for the Prieſts and Leuites thoſe which ought rather to haue preuented him, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them to caſt forth the filthines. By filthines he meant all kinds of ſtrange ſeruices. All what was not in the law, that counted he to be ſtrange; &amp; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they might haue ſaid, as we at this day; haue not our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers liued as wel as thou? what wilt thou the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do? He cutteth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhort with this, <hi>our fathers haue trespaſſed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Chron. 29. v. 6.7.</note> 
               <hi>and done evill in the eies of the Lord our God, &amp; haue turned away their faces from him and turned their backs; they haue quenched the lampes of the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple:</hi> What light the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can we look
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:13226:45"/>for, or what darknes ought not we to expect from them? And therefore did they ariſe at this word, and gathered their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and being convicted and ſorrowfull in their hearts ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified themſelues, cleanſed the houſe of the Lord, &amp; caried the filth therof out vnto the brook; that it might neuer at any time be remembred. And all this was done according to the comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of the king, as it is ſaide there? But what is added?<note place="margin">V. 15.</note> 
               <hi>By the word of the Lord:</hi> as before was ſaid of <hi>Ioſaphat.</hi> And that for to aboliſh all falſe worſhippings. He beginneth afterwarde to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſh the true worſhip, &amp; the maner of their ſacrifices, by the ſame authority, and in the like method, <hi>according to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>man<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dement,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>of David, and Gad, and Nathan.</hi>
               <note place="margin">V 25.</note> This might ſeeme enough to content them,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:13226:46"/>ſeeing theſe were ſuch excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t prophets. But doth he ſtay there and thinketh he therby to haue ſatisfied them? No, but he takes it yet higher. In the church of God, wherein we muſt not liue after examples or the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements of men; <hi>for the comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement,</hi> ſaith he,<note place="margin">V. 25.</note> 
               <hi>was by the hand of the Lord, &amp; by the hand of his Prophets.</hi> And wee muſt not thinke that al this while <hi>Heze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah</hi> was attended vpon or aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted by others in that manner, as ſo good a worke might haue required. The Prieſts, in the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie reformation of theſe ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, are found to be but fewe in number. Thoſe, which haue the chiefeſt charge in the church, are not alwaies the firſt that do reforme it: for want of them, he was conſtained to ſet a worke <hi>the Levites;</hi> wee in our daies might ſay for want of Biſhops,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:13226:46"/>the Prieſts or Deacons, thoſe which are leſſe bounde to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent and forbid theſe corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. <hi>The Levites,</hi> ſaith the holy ſtory, being found <hi>to be,</hi>
               <note place="margin">V. 34. &amp; 35</note> 
               <hi>more vp right in heart for to ſanctifie the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, then the Prieſts, &amp;c: And ſo the ſervice of the houſe of the Lord was ſet in order.</hi> In the like maner doth <hi>Hezekiah</hi> proceed to the reformation of the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts; he publiſheth a paſſeover to be kept throughout al Iſrael and that ſuch a paſſeover, ſaith the authour of this holy ſtorie, <hi>as for a long time before they had not celebrated, after that manner as it is written,</hi> to wit, in the law of God. For a long time before, ſaith he; This might haue beene enough to ſtop all reformation; and if we had liued at that time, wee had bin ready to tell them, haue not our fathers done it on this manner? Are they all dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned?
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:13226:47"/>What need is there then of ſuch a change? will we be wiſer then they? wifer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Prieſts? wifer then the church it ſelfe? But what then would <hi>Hezeki<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah</hi> haue told vs? The ſame truly, that he told them:<note place="margin">2. Chron. 30.16.</note> 
               <hi>Ye children of Iſraell, turne againe vnto the Lord God of Abraham, Iſaac, &amp; Iacob.</hi> It is no time now to ſtay ſtill in theſe Abuſes. And he cau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed this to be cried every where throughout the land.<note place="margin">V. 7.</note> 
               <hi>Be not yee like your fathers &amp; like your bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, which trespaſſed againſt the Lorde God of their fathers.</hi> What proportion, I pray you, is there betweene that reſpect, which you owe to your earthly fathers, and that duety, which you owe to the Lorde God of you and of your fathers alſo? There were not wanting, ſaith be ſome men in Ephraim, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſen, and Zebulun, that moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:13226:47"/>them, being now growne old in their filthines; neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe the greater part ſubmitted themſelues: In Iudah eſpecially, with one heart,<note place="margin">V. 12.</note> 
               <hi>according to the word of the Lord.</hi> They take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way therefore the altars that were in Ieruſalem, and all thoſe for incenſe tooke they away, &amp; they celebrated the paſſeouer, according to the Law. Some at legth of the Prieſts <hi>were aſha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ed, &amp; ſanctified the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelus,</hi> the Levits ſupplying the places and the du<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty of thoſe that were obſtinate againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And the like thing the like paſſeover, <hi>was not ſeene in Ieruſalem ſince the time of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon and of David,</hi>
               <note place="margin">V. 26.</note> for many a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges together. And it followeth in the ſame place, that aſſoone as the paſſeover was finiſhed, by the ſame commaundement, all the people being inflamed with a new zeale, went out, and
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:13226:48"/>brake the images, &amp; cut downe the groues, and brake downe the high places and the altars. But behold, they did more yet; at the ſame time alſo, (for it is to be read in the ſame verſe, the Authour maketh not two nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of this and that which went before,<note place="margin">2 King 18 v 4. Numb. 21 v. 9.</note>) <hi>he brake in pieces the braſen ſerpent that Moſes had made</hi> by the expreſſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement of God, for a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent remedy againſt the bitings of thoſe fiery ſerpents, to him that did looke on it; as a ſigne of Chriſt the Son of God, which was to be lifted vp on a tree, for a remedy againſt ſin, the biting of that old ſerpent, to him that would turn the eies of his faith towards him. Becauſe that now indeede, of that preſent vſe, which remained no lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ey had made an abuſe: of the ſigne and ſacrament of Chriſt which
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:13226:48"/>was to come, they had made it as the thing it ſelfe, and had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven vnto it divine honours: and had laſtly converted this ſo healthfull an image into an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominable idoll. Wherefore al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, when he brake it, hee gaue them to vnderſtand, that it was but <hi>Nehuſhtan,</hi> a piece of braſſe contemptible in it ſelfe, &amp; here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after for ever vnprofitable, I &amp; da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gerous too, by reaſon of that relation which it had vnto Chriſt, ſeeing they abuſed it. And hee was very highly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended for it by the Spirit of God, for hauing <hi>done vprightly in the ſight of the Lord,</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>he truſted in the God of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raell:</hi> for having laid aſide al hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane conſiderations, that hee might retaine or reſtore the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of his ſervice. And indeede by reaſon of the conditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the church wherein wee obſerued
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:13226:49"/>hir to haue bin at that time, as alſo by reaſon of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nivence the ſlacknes and corruption of the Prieſts, which then were; it is not to bee doubred, but that he met with ſome that contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted him; &amp; then is it not ſaid here for naught, <hi>that hee truſted</hi> in <hi>God,</hi> to wit, againſt the mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muring of the people; And, <hi>vnto thoſe daies the children of Iſraell burned incenſe to it;</hi> alleadging without doubt, a preſcriptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſo many yeares, but eſpecially, that this ſerpent was inſtituted by God and erected by <hi>Moſes</hi> himſelf. But againſt all this, that anſwere which our Savior gaue here to the Phariſie; ſtood him inſteede: <hi>Non ſic fuit ab mitio, From the beginning it was not ſo.</hi> It was ordained to be a remedy for you againſt the biting of he ſerpents in the wilderneſſe; and now you are no longer in that
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:13226:49"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſe. For a ſigne, that on that Chriſt which was to come, the ſonne of the liuing God, did de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pend all your health both tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall and ſpirituall; and you now haue attributed all that to this image, and transferred the honour of the Creatour to the creature, of the ordeiner him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to the thing ordeined by him. And therfore hath he now brought it backe againe to his firſt nature. And I woulde to God we had not many thinges in our Chriſtian Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which haue very great need of the like remedie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ioſiah</hi> likewiſe is renoumed amongſt the kings of Iſrael,<note place="margin">2 Chron. 34. &amp;. 35.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee had reformed the church: &amp; that on good grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds for <hi>Manaſſeh</hi> had defiled all the ſervice thereof, &amp; had brought in falſe Gods in ſteed of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie, and <hi>Amon</hi> his ſon, the
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:13226:50"/>father of <hi>Ioſiah,</hi> had not done much better then he.<note place="margin">2 King. 22 &amp; 23.</note> 
               <hi>Ioſiah</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan this reformation, by repai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the ruines of the Temple, whereof he laide the charge on <hi>Hilkiah</hi> the high Prieſt. It hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened ſo, that <hi>Hilkiah</hi> amongſt many other old regiſters,<note place="margin">2 King, 22</note> which he ſought for, found the booke of the Law in the Temple. You may imagine to what a ſtraight the church was brought, when the high Prieſt himſelfe findeth this booke but by a chance. No ſooner had he found it, but hee ſendeth it to <hi>Ioſiah</hi> by <hi>Shaphan</hi> the Secretarie, which read it be fore him; therein hee findeth, that it was a thing of nothing to build vp againe the Temple of God, vnleſſe hee alſo would eſtabliſh againe his ſeruice; that it rained not only on the ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe top, as they ſay; but that the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide alſo was poſaned, and the
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:13226:50"/>Sanctuarie filled with Idolatry. And hereupon beginneth hee nowe to deteſt the ſinne of the Church: rent his cloathes, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth counſell with the Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſe, and humbleth himſelfe. Here the Prieſt might haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted himſelfe with this: that he knew his leſſon by hearte, &amp; might haue contented him with the tradition of the Church; which neuer faileth, never lieth; but what do'es he? He gathereth together the Prieſts and the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vits in the houſe of God; all Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da, all Ieruſalem, <hi>from the verie leaſt to the greateſt.</hi> At that time was it not the faſhion to get a diſpenſation for to read the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures? In the middeſt of them all he cauſeth this booke to bee read: which being read, hee maketh a couenant to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue it, and bindeth therewith all the people. And after al this,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:13226:51"/>he purgeth the Temple from all idolatrie and ſuperſtition, and driueth out al the Prieſts there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, hee caſteth their veſſels into the fire, and breaketh down the high places, euen thoſe that were in the cities of Iuda, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing beene tolerated by ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny good kings, &amp; in the which the Prieſts of the ſtock of Leui thoſe that had their lawfull cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, did ſacrifice vnto the true God. And hereupo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there might haue beene much to gaineſay: what is there wanting to theſe ſacrifices? Are they not offered to him and by thoſe, to whome and by whom they ought to be offered? Is this therefore any thing elſe, but a deſire of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veltie. And put the caſe, that there is ſome defect in them, is it not for all that tolerable, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving already beene tolerated by ſo many good kings, by ſo
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:13226:51"/>many high Prieſts, for ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny yeares to gether? And is it not in this, that that law of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy is to take place, that a thing once well ſetled, though it bee euill, ought not to bee taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, but to ſhun all inconueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences it ought to be left ſtill in his place? And neuertheles our rule makes him not ſticke at all this;<note place="margin">Deut. 12, v. 11.</note> 
               <hi>From the beginning it was not ſo. There ſhall be a place</hi> (ſaith Moſes) <hi>which the Lord ſhal chuſe to cauſe his name to dwell there; thither ſhall you bring all your burnt offerings and your ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, &amp;c. Take heed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">V. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>that thou of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer them not in every place that thou ſeeſt,</hi> and which thou thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt to be fit for thy purpoſe. As if he ſaid, for I will not take any of thy pretended ſupererogati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for ſacrifices or worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping. I will be worſhiped, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that which I haue
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:13226:52"/>commanded thee, and not after thine owne fanſie. Becauſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed that God, the very reaſon and cauſe of all things, hath his end in all whatſoeuer he ordei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth; for to direct all nations to the ſacrifice of his onlie ſonne alone, hee would haue but one temple, one ſanctuarie, and one altar, whereas thou doſt darken and confound his meaning, by thine owne inventions, by thy pretended good purpoſes, and by ſuch a multitude of thine high places and thine altars; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very ſacrifice of thine is a wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g worſhip. Therefore alſo is it ſaid, in that which followes; that he commanded the people to keep the Paſſeover. But how? <hi>As it is written in the booke of the covenant;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Kin. c. 23</note> 
               <hi>according to the word of the Lord delivered by the hand of Moſes.</hi> He ſendeth them to the originall, to the old form
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:13226:52"/>thereof; and indeed it is added, <hi>There was no Paſſeover holden like that from the daies of the Iudges that iudged Iſraell,</hi>
               <note place="margin">V. 22.</note> 
               <hi>nor in all the daies of the kings of Iſraell and of the kings of Iuda;</hi> not in Samuels time, no nor in the time of Hezekiah himſelfe. So neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie a thing did hee eſteeme it, to keepe himſelfe exactly to the law of the Lord, and to his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures.</p>
            <p>In the time of the captiuitie of Babylon, the Church of God, Gods Iſraell, in the midſt of the Chaldeans, thoſe great maſters of ceremonies and patrons of al idolatrie and ſuperſtition, could not poſſibly haue ſtood out ſo long without being corrupted. What does then Eſdras in this caſe, when he bringeth back the people into Ieruſalem? Howe doth he proceed to ſet them in order againe? Truely it is ſaid
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:13226:53"/>that, as ſoon as they were come into Ieruſalem, Ieſhua the ſon of Iozadak, with his brethren the Prieſts, and Zerubbabel the ſonne of Salathiel, the captaine of the tranſmigration, <hi>Builded the altar of the God of Iſraell to offer thereon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſd 3 v. 2</note> not according to their owne fanſy, nor according to that which they might haue learned in that medlie of the heathen; but, ſaith hee, <hi>as it is written in the law of Moſes, the man of God.</hi> As if it were ſaid, that they calling to minde the puniſhment of the ſonnes of Aaron, which were conſumed by the fire of the wrath of God, for hauing offered vnto him a ſtrange fire; they reeſtabliſh af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſame manner the ſervice of God in Ieruſalem, <hi>as it is written in the booke of Moſes;</hi> they are not aſhamed to go and learne their leſſon therein. And
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:13226:53"/>yet are wee not to thinke, that they wanted amongſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuch men as were of courage, and had in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> preſumptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> enough, to adde ſomewhat of their own therevnto. Laſtly, to apply ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what neerer our text to this pur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſe; Eſdras the reſtorer of the Church at that time, was fully informed, how that many of the cheefeſt of the people, yea &amp; ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e Prieſts alſo againſt the expreſſe law of the Lord, had taken vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to themſelues ſtrange wiues,<note place="margin">Chap. 9.</note> of thoſe nations which were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden them; whereupon hee rent his clothes, pluckt of the haire of his heade and of his beard, fell on his knees, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed both his owne and the peoples ſinnes in the preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of God;<note place="margin">V. 7.</note> 
               <hi>from the daies of our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>haue wee beene in a great treſpaſſe vnto this day.</hi> The longer that the ſinne had
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:13226:54"/>laſted, the greater doth hee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge to bee the fault: ſo farre was he from taking there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by any right occaſion to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue it. But did he ſtay here only? No, he returned<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to his principle; <hi>Thou hadſt forbidden vs to do ſo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Levit 18. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 25 27.</note> ſaith he, <hi>by thy ſervants the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 7.3.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And now <hi>ſhall wee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to breake theſe commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments?</hi> Shall wee goe on ſtil, ô Lord, in theſe abominations? So that being ſtrengthned by the aſſiſtance of honeſt men, &amp; amongſt others by Shechaniah the ſonne of Iehiel, hee cauſed the people to ſweare &amp; bound them with a newe oath to the keeping of Gods law, that lawe eſpecially, which forbad all theſe inceſtes; whence enſued forth with the putting away of all their ſtrange wiues, and that by the common conſent of the people and of the Prieſts them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues,
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:13226:54"/>which at the reading of the law were convicted of their faults. This was a hard ſentence you will ſay, as alſo an harder execution, to part aſunder ſo many houſholds, and to rent in two the wife from the huſband, the children from the mother. And what became then all this while of Eſdras his wiſdome? Was there no Pope amongſt them in thoſe daies, that might haue diſpenſed with them for this? But rather if thou beleeveſt the Lord, when he hath ſpoken, wouldſt thou haue had him caſt Gods people againe into that furnace from whence they were but newly come; and that <hi>the wrath of the Lord</hi> for diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence (they are the very wordes of the law) <hi>ſhould waxhot againſt them,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, 4.</note> 
               <hi>and deſtroy them ſuddenly?</hi> So certaine is that maxime in al good divinitie, that wee ought
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:13226:55"/>to obey God without looking back; and in a matter of refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation we ought to do nothing by roate, but haue alwaies re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe vnto this booke.</p>
            <p>Our Lord therefore, which was come in our fleſh to reform the Church, doth giue vs alſo the ſame rule, a rule indeed pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced by him in this one caſe; but yet it extendeth it ſelfe over all whatſoever concernes Gods ſervice, and therefore is it here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſo much the more to bee put in practiſe, as this is a matter of greater myſterie and weight. As alſo we learne the ſame in Gods law concerning his ſervice. So ſaith he in another place, where hee inſtructeth his Diſciples: <hi>Thinke not that I am come to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the law or the Prophets:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 5. v. 17.</note> The reformation of the church hath alwaies bin ſubiect to this ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. I am come to fulfil them, to
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:13226:55"/>recal the law vnto his right ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, to reſtore vnto it his due and natural interpretation, and to keepe it from all traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, inventions, and Phariſaical gloſſes, the which vnder a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of giuing light vnto it, doe indeed darken it: inſteede of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhing it, doe deſtroy it; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteed of honouring it, doe make a mocke of it. You haue hearde that it was ſaide by them of the old time, your Doctors, &amp; your Fathers, <hi>Thou ſhalt not kill, for whoſoever killeth ſhall bee culpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of iudgement.</hi>
               <note place="margin">V. 21.</note> For to avoide this iudgment they haue taught you, that it was enough not to kill at all; likewiſe it was ſaide; <hi>Thou ſhalt not commit adulterie.</hi>
               <note place="margin">V. 27.</note> And they haue made you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, that you were free from this law, if only you kept your ſelues from acting this ſin. Like wiſe;<note place="margin">V. 43.</note> 
               <hi>Thou ſhalt loue thy neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:13226:56"/>and hate thine enemie.</hi> And in like manner all the other co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements. But <hi>I ſay vnto you</hi> I that am the true law giuer, that knowe the meaning of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, of that eternall Father, the creatour of bodies and ſpirites, which giveth his lawe alike to the one and to the other; That whoſoever hateth his brother hath already killed him; whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever looketh on a woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to luſt after hir, hath already commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted adultery with her. And, if ſo be you do not helpe your grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt enemies, euen thoſe which perſecute you, then are you not his children, but the children of hell. Calling them backe in this manner from their Fathers (as we haue obſerved throughout in the ſtate of the church of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raell) to the God of their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the gloſſe, to the text; from the letter, to the ſpirit, to
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:13226:56"/>the right purpoſe of the Law gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, &amp; to the reaſon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the law. And this did the Phariſies ſaie we, to blaſpheme the Temple, and to call <hi>Moſes</hi> in queſtion; in theſe daies amongſt vs men would ſay it were, to condemne the Fathers, and to overthrowe the Church. Behold therefore this rule, which our Sauiour gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth vs: <hi>from the beginning it was not ſo.</hi> This was not the will of him that made the Teſtament; let this rule but bee ſtretched out over the building of the church; and then, whatſoever ſhall be found to bee out of this line, or out of the ſquire, let it be cenſured to be alſo out of the worke, let it bee condemned to be battered by the hammer, and to be cut of from the faith &amp; do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctrine of the church. Let <hi>S. Paul</hi> bee an example vnto vs even in thoſe firſt times. For men, in
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:13226:57"/>matters of religion, can never go on very farre without ſtray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, vnleſſe they alwaies take this guide along with them. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in his time was the holy ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the Lord prophaned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the <hi>Corinthians;</hi> in this <hi>church of God,</hi> by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>that were ſanctified in Chriſt Ieſus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cor. 1.2.</note> and <hi>Saints by calling:</hi> for ſo hee tear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth them. But what ſaith he to them? <hi>Everie man, when they ſhould eate,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 11. v. 21</note> 
               <hi>taketh his owne ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per afore, &amp;c. And one is hungry and another is drunken. This is not to eat the Lords Supper.</hi> This is not to celebrate that holy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, it is rather to deſpiſe his church. Here then is a reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die for it. <hi>I haue received,</hi> ſaith he <hi>of the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">V. 23</note> 
               <hi>that which I alſo haue delivered or taught vnto you.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Theodor i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 1. de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.7</note> And herevpon doth hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſe vnto them at large the whole inſtitution of the Lords
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:13226:57"/>Supper, in the ſame manner as we finde it in the Goſpell; As I haue receiued it, euen ſo haue I delivered it vnto you; It is now your dutie, if you will be Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, to obſerue it according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. <hi>S. Peter</hi> alſo perceiving that hee was nowe ſhortly to leaue this worlde,<note place="margin">Gelaſ. Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lic. in Act. Conc. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ic</note> doth not tell the churches to the which he wrot; after my deceaſe, doe not much trouble your ſelues about that which you are to do; I will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct you ſufficiently by reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, and viſions; there ſhall ſcarce bee one weeke in the which I will not giue you ſome new Article of faith, or deliuer vnto you ſome new ceremonie or other. But on the contrarie he ſaith; <hi>Seeing I know that the time is at hand, that I muſt laie downe this my tabernacle,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Pet 1. v. 14, &amp; 15.</note> 
               <hi>I will indevour therefore alwaies, that after my departing ye alſo may be
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:13226:58"/>able to haue reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance of theſe things,</hi> that is, of the doctrine of ſaluation, <hi>which openeth vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an entrance into the everlaſting kingdome of Chriſt Ieſus.</hi> To wit I my ſelfe beating this doctrine into you ſo deepe, whileſt I am yet amongſt you in this Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle, that, after I ſhall haue left you, you ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not forget it. Which alſo was the reaſon, why that great Emperor Conſtantine in the middeſt of all the hard con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions of his time went no where for helpe but thither. <hi>There is nothing more vnworthy</hi> ſaid he to the Biſhoppes of his time, <hi>then to wrangle one with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother about the controverſies of divine matters, ſeeing that vvee haue the doctrin of the holy Ghoſt in writing.</hi> And, <hi>the bookes of the Evangeliſts and Apoſtles, togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the Oracles of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Prophets, doe teach vs evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:13226:58"/>what we ought to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude about divine matters, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore laying aſide all diſcord, let vs take the deciſion of all our contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies out of thoſe words, which were inspired by God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What then? Is it now behoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to reduce the Chriſtian Church to this rule? The church truely hath alwaies fitly beene compared to a ſhip: and no ſhip can keep his right way without a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſe to direct it; if at ſome time it be not looked vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, how good and skilfull ſoeuer the Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot or the Mates of the ſhip be, we are not to think it ſtrange, if ſhee bee much out of the waie. This ſhip alſo hath floted vp &amp; downe for many yeares toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and hath run vpon manie ſtrange coaſts: it were then a marveile, if ſhe were not ſoiled, or had not gathered on the out ſide much moſſe, many wormes
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:13226:59"/>and ſhels; &amp; in the inſide much corruption, contagion, and all kindes of vermine; or if ſhee did not leake for a long time alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy on ſo many places, where e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one bringeth his ſuperflui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, &amp; leaueth his excrements, but no man in all this time hath taken the beaſom in hand or ſet hand to the Pumpe. It were a miracle indeed if there had bin left any thing entire. And wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that we are, being our ſelues full of naſtineſſe in the midſt of all this filth; yet do we cry out blaſphemy, if anie one ſmell it; and curſe him, that will take it away. Shee hath moiled hir anker within the have<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, yea and in the mud alſo and owze, of Iewes, Pagans, Philoſophers Peripatetiks, Academikes, both old and new. Shee hath beene fraighted with their marchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, with their inventions. Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:13226:59"/>the one, ſhe hath put on the ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, which from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth ore without any myſterie; and from the others, ſhee hath borrowed their ſuperſtition &amp; Idolatry: from the one, by a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible imitation, ſhe hath confir<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med the preſumption &amp; merits of man, contrary to the ende of the whole law and Goſpell; fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the others they haue receiued fables for truth, Poëſies for hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory, Mythology for Diuinity: for theſe tenne or twelue hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeares togither, we haue had no other trade, no other tra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ficke, beeing alwaies mingled, (like vnto the people of Iſraell, not once looking on the lawe) with ſtrange women; &amp; yet doe we finde it ſtrange, that our pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geny, our religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, is become ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtard? can we beleeue, if the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles of our Lorde, if all thoſe Apoſtolicall men, of the nexte
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:13226:60"/>age, ſhould come hither once a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, that they would finde as much as one ſtep of the old diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline and Chriſtian policie; A<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mongſt vs truly hath now been verified that tale, which goeth about, of him that tooke a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner, but was caried away by him himſelfe. We haue conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted many Iews and Pagans vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſt; but they haue perver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vs: we haue baptized them; but they haue plunged vs in their filthines: and from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth, if we now convert one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>em, wee make them twiſe as much the ſons of hell.</p>
            <p>Come thou then hither, and queſtion with our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt, not as a Phariſie to te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt him, but as a true Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with a good conſcience to learne of him. Maſter, teach me how to pray; I know, that I ought to cal vpon God, but I am told, that I
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:13226:60"/>ought alſo to call vpon the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels and Saints, and ſet them a work as interceſſers vnto thee. Is this lawfull? He will tell thee with out doubt, (for he cannot do otherwiſe, being neither co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to God nor to himſelfe,) Haſt thou not read, that which is written; <hi>Call vpon me, and I will heare thee, &amp; thou ſhalt giue me the praiſe.</hi> And knoweſt thou not that hee, in whom men be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, is one only God, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to thy Creed, the Father, the Sonne, and the holy Ghoſt? And howe often is it rehearſed vnto thee, that there is but <hi>one only Mediator betweene God &amp; men:</hi> he alone, that could make their peace with the Father and their propitiation in his blood? And herevpon as thy Phariſies, thou canſt not chooſe but make reply on this manner: why then doth ſuch or ſuch a father direct
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:13226:61"/>vs to this or to that Martyr? But he will anſwere vs againe: For the hardnes of your hart, &amp; out of the weakneſſe of theirs, was this ſo done. You come but new and freſh from the ſervice of falſe Gods; Theſe good men thought then to haue gained much, when they had cauſed you to put the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> away, &amp; to take the Saints for a change inſteede of them; <hi>But from the beginning it was not ſo.</hi> For the ſpace of 4. or 5. thouſand yeares togither, men ſpake not of calling vpon any other in the church, but on God alone; the Angels were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>verſant with the Patriarks: doth any one cal vpon them? <hi>Henoch</hi> and <hi>Eliah</hi> were taken vp into heauen; <hi>Noe</hi> or his children, <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſha</hi> or his other diſciples, doe they come vnto them? Of ſo many Pſalmes of <hi>David,</hi> which are as ſo many praiers, in al that
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:13226:61"/>diverſity of matter, is there anie one only that hath any other obiect of his faith, and of his praier, but him alone? And am I come to derogate from his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, I the beloued Son from the Fathers worſhip, or rather to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſh it, &amp; ſo much the more to glorifie him? I then tell you that which I long ſince tolde to Sathan; <hi>Thou ſhalt worſhippe the Lord thy God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Marth. 4.</note> 
               <hi>and him only ſhalt thou ſerue.</hi> And invocation is one of the chiefe partes of his worſhip, of his ſervice. Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the weaknes of ſome of my ſerva<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts do not you take al your ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ght: out of their wants, doe not you ſeeke a ſupply either of the law of God, or of my Goſpell: and from my patience by reaſon of my long forbearance, doe not you make a law, nor thinke to pleade preſcription againſt the true religion and pure worſhip.
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:13226:62"/>That which the Lorde hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued vnto himſelfe alone, doe not you turne it away vpon the creature, do not part it.</p>
            <p>Let another come, and ſaie thus; Maſter, we are al in doubt amidſt al theſe controverſies. Is it lawfull to reverence, to adore the Images of the Saints, of the Virgin <hi>Marie,</hi> thine owne, that alſo of the holy Trinitie? And he will anſwere doubtleſſe, hee which is come to eſtabliſh the law and not do deſtroy it; Haſt thou not read what is writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the law; in that law, which was given by the miniſterie of the holy Angels? <hi>Thou ſhalt not make any grave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> image;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 20.</note> 
               <hi>thou ſhalt not bow downe to them, neither ſerue them.</hi> Doeſt thou not look for ſome plainer or more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe ſpeech? Or is it need, that you ſhould haue a gloſſe here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon? There followes therefore
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:13226:62"/>the reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of it. For ſaith he, I am the Lord thy God; a mighty &amp; iealous God. And can his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture then be changed now? And yet thou wilt not bee aſhamed to reply: why the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue our Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto vs for books inſteed of the Goſpels? When we guild them, cloth them, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fume them, worſhip them, call vpon them; is there any thing in all this, wherof God may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine? To whom doth this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour redounde but to him, his Saints beeing glorified in their images, &amp; he in his Saintes? But know thou (will he anſwere thee) that God, as he is a Spirit, ſo he will haue ſuch as worſhip him in ſpirit and truth; he wilbe worſhipped, as he himſelfe hath commanded, and not after the fanſies of men. Know alſo that an image is a teacher of lies,<note place="margin">Habak. 2, v. 18.</note> and maketh of men beaſts, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:13226:63"/>thoſe that are inclined therevnto; and as for thoſe Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters that haue giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you images inſteede of Maſters, they did this ſince the time that they are become ignorant and careleſſe and haue bin diſpenſed withall for not preaching my Goſpell, dumbe Paſtors as they were themſelues they haue give<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thee theſe dumbe preachers. <hi>But fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the beginning it was not ſo,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the law and vnder the law, for the ſpace of fower thouſand yeares, the church of God hath had no images. To haue them or not to haue them, as ſome particular liverie, did then put a difference betweene the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuer and the infidell. Yea and for eight hundred yeares toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſince the time that by mee grace was come into the world in the better part of Europe, in France it ſelfe, there were none
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:13226:63"/>of them. I therefore ſay vnto you. Of the ignorance of your Maſters doe not you make your knowledge; make not your Chriſtianitie of the imitation and emulation of Paganiſme; The word of the Lord ſtandeth faſt for ever. That which once he hath ordained, hee never ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perannuateth nor diſanulleth.</p>
            <p>Let another proceed, I know Lord, that thou art the Lambe, which takeſt away the ſinnes of the world. But wee are told alſo of a certaine fire, at our going out of this world, wherein wee muſt be purged, and muſt for all this pay and make euen our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koning; what muſt I beleeue in this matter? And therevpon hee will tell thee all that, which the holy Scripture teacheth vs: haſt thou not read, what my Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets ſay, That <hi>I was woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for your tranſgreſſions,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſai. 53. v, 5.</note> 
               <hi>and
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:13226:64"/>broken for your iniquities, &amp; that the chaſtiſeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of your peace was vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me.</hi> God which is al iuſtice, all mercy, will he haue the ſame debt paid twiſe? Zacharie ſaith, <hi>There ſhall be a fountaine opened to the houſe of David,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zacharie. 13. v. 1.</note> to the Church, <hi>for ſinne,</hi> for every vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleaneſſe whatſoeuer; and I ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily am this fountaine, a foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine that neuer dryeth vppe; to what purpoſe ſerues thy fire if this water doe ſuffice? And that this water is not ſufficient, who can ſay it without blaſphemie. But yet if thou wilt haue a fire alſo, heare what Iohn the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt ſaith;<note place="margin">Matth.</note> I baptize thee with wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter and with fire. Thy ſpirit in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed with a ſpirituall fire, euen with mine own ſpirit. And here thou wilt reply (for thou art for bidden to yeeld) But S. Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine, and S. Gregorie doe not they ſpeak of a fire, to the which
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:13226:64"/>wee muſt goe when wee depart out of this world? Doe not they ſay, thee it is not altogether in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible that there is one, and that it may be true? And at all aduentures hath it not beene a good thing to keepe the ſoules in ſuch aw? For how many faire Churches haue beene founded thereby, how many cloiſters, Chappels, and Maſſes? And will you then haue the olde doubts of thoſe men to be vnto you as articles of faith? The fables of Platonikes as truth? The fictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of Poets, as ſound diuinitie? Our Lorde moreouer will ſay vnto thee. He that beleeueth in the Sonne, hath life euerlaſting, he is already gon from death to life; hee that beleeueth not in him, the wrath of God remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth vpon him; hee is already condemned, and ſhall not ſee life. Betweene theſe two where
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:13226:65"/>canſt thou finde any place for this Purgatorie? And then will the Sonne of God ſay vnto thee againe; Do not ſtand vpon that which the Doctours tell thee thereof; They could never cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate it. <hi>From the beginning it was not ſo.</hi> If it had beene from the beginning, there is no queſtion but the Church of Iſraell would haue made vſe of it; by ſo much the more, becauſe that foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, for the cleanſing of ſinne, was not as then opened. And yet for foure thouſand yeares together, is there any one word ſpoken of it? Amongſt ſo many ſacrifices, and thoſe of ſo many faſhions; is there any one word ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſuch ſacrifices, as were for the dead or for their ſinnes? And if it had been created ſince that time, would then the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles haue hidden it from vs? would they haue told vs. <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:13226:65"/>are they that die in the Lord, from henceforth they do reſt from their labours. If wee confeſſe our ſinnes God is faithfull and iuſt; The blood of his Son Ieſus Chriſt doth purge and cleanſe vs from all ſinne.</hi> This Purgatorie then is a ſtrange fire in the Church; ſuch a one, as quencheth her na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>turall heate, her confidence in the merit of the Redeemer. And therefore; That which the Lord hath paid and quitted for vs ſo dearely, ſo fully, the faithfull ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> needs not to buy it againe; Let no ſervant of God therefore ſel it him againe.</p>
            <p>Let another alſo come, that perhaps hath looked more dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pely into it; and ſay, Maſter, I knowe that thou haſt bin made an oblation on the tree of the Croſſe, &amp; wiped out, and vtterly aboliſhed the handwriting that was againſt vs. And neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:13226:66"/>we are told, that thou art every day offered vp, euery day ſacrificed in Maſſe; and herevp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is all this ſtirre; To what o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion therefore ſhall we ſtand faſt? and hereupo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he wil tel thee Haſt thou not read, what Eſay ſaith of me; <hi>His ſoule ſhall bee made an oblation for ſinne;</hi> The ſoule of the Sonne of God. At what rate the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doſt thou reckon her? and knoweſt thou not that I haue giuen my fleſh for the life, and my blood for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of the ſins of the world? In compariſon of this price, all your pretended. Oblations can amount to nothing. Knoweſt thou not alſo, that likewiſe all the other ſacriſices of the Law, are fulfilled and aboliſhed in this one onely? And here, either blown vp by tradition, or fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtalled by cuſtome, thou wilt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply; but would then our Fathers
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:13226:66"/>for ſo long time together haue made ſo great account of the Maſſe, and all for nothing? Why then, art thou not then, really with thy fleſh and bones, ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficed therein every day? Did not men ſpeake of this oblation, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in the time of good S. Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorie, not aboue ſix hundred yeares after thine incarnation. The ill diſpoſed facilitie of men in accommodating themſelues to infidelitie, hath brought in theſe things; And this carnall wiſdome, hath beene found to be but naturall, and is rightly convicted of folly before God. The outward worſhip of Iewes and Gentiles conſiſted in ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices; and when they haue been brought to the Chriſtian faith, they were willing to content them with the word of ſacrifice taken in a large ſenſe; with this word did they qualifie the chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:13226:67"/>ſervice; their prayers, their Sacraments, their Almes. How farre ſafer had it beene, to keep them in their owne proprietie; and to teach them the right end of the old ſacrifices; that is, their end in my cone only Sacrifice? I had alſo appointed for a ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of this one ſa crifice, of my fleſh cruciſied and of my blood ſhed for you, <hi>That bread which you break,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Cor. 10 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 16.</note> 
               <hi>the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of my bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; that cup which you bleſſe, the Communion of my blood.</hi> The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all communication in ſumme of all the bleſſings and beneſittes, that redound vnto you by this ſacrifice. And in as much as their devotion did wax cold, inſtead of making my people partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate of them, they haue thought it enough onely to ſhe we them vnto them, they haue alſo taken my cup from them. But I ſay vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, that <hi>From the beginning
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:13226:67"/>it was not ſo.</hi> Do but read the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle; <hi>Without ſheading of blood is no remiſſion of ſinne.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb 9. v. 22.</note> And wilt thou therefore for the remiſſion of thy ſinnes take vnto thy ſelfe the place of the Iewes; wilt thou once againe ſhedde my blood? Read on further that which hee rehearſeth vnto thee ſo often; Chriſt <hi>hath appeared once to put away ſinne by the ſacrifice of him ſelfe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">V. 26.</note> It is not then for nought, that they ſhewe him ſo manie times vnto thee? Againe, <hi>We are ſanctified by the offering of the bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy of Ie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſus Chriſt once made.</hi>
               <note place="margin">C. 10. v. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0</note> 
               <hi>With one offering hath hee conſecrated vs for ever.</hi> and iffoneuer,<note place="margin">V. 14.</note> why then doe we begin againe eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day? That therefore, which I haue fulfilled at once, effectual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and perfectly, doe not thou accuſe it of imperfection by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iterating it; doe not darken the truth, nor belie the vertue ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:13226:68"/>by the friuolous repre ſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. That which I haue giuen thee for a Sacrament, &amp; thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving, of that vnſpeakable be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſit, do not thou account it as a Sacrifice. That which God hath ioined, ſeeing I haue ioin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them, to wit, the ſacraments in my holy Supper; thou man, vnder what colour ſoeuer it be, do not ſeparate them.</p>
            <p>But laſtly, could our Fathers then overſee ſo groſly? Theſe good kings, <hi>Ioſaphat, Hezekiah Iozia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> thoſe good ſervantes of God, <hi>Hilkiah, Eſdras,</hi> &amp; others, did never make this queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they had the booke of the law, and did know, that therein they had the ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces of God, they rent their clothes, beate their breaſtes, confeſſed both their owne &amp; their fathers ſins before the Congre gation; they exhorted, and by their own ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:13226:68"/>brought, the whole peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to repentance. What there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, coulde our Saviour euer leaue vs as Orphanes, and his barke without a guide? On the contrary, hath he not left vs a lieuetena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t general, a vice-God, this man God on earth? Elſe what becomes of that, <hi>Tues Pe trus, Paſce oves meas, Thou art Peter:</hi> and, <hi>feed my ſheepe.</hi> But here our Lord wil anſwer thee. I am that everlaſting word, that was made fleſh for thee. The on ly Emmanuell, God with thee; <hi>with you,</hi> by my Spirit in mine holy word; <hi>I am with you vntill the end of the world.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th. 28</note> As for lieue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenants, I haue as many, as there are good Paſtors and holy diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſers of my word and Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments here on earth. But as for Generall, or Vice-God, there ought none to be over my ſtate becauſe I am every where pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent,
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:13226:69"/>I haue no need of any; how much ſo ever the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be limited to a certaine place, or be he as quick as he wil or is able to be. I haue ſaid indeode vnto <hi>Peter,</hi> one of mine Apoſtles, and vnto one for all. <hi>Thou art Peter, &amp; on this Rocke wil I build my church.</hi> On this Rocke, that is, on his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> feſſion; for he had confeſſed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me,<note place="margin">Matth. 16</note> 
               <hi>Thou art the Chriſt the ſon of the living God.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon haue you placed vnder an Altar at Rome, the ſuppoſed Re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liques of <hi>Peter,</hi> and haue called them the confeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of <hi>Peter.</hi> On this pretended confeſſion haue you built <hi>S. Peters</hi> church. It was not ſo that this holy Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle vnderſtood it, when he told vs,<note place="margin">Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 2. v. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Be yee as liuely ſtones made a spirituall houſe.</hi> But vpon what? truly not vpon this your co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, but vpon his owne, <hi>vpon him that is that living ſtone,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:13226:69"/>by me, and yet the <hi>chiefe Corner-ſtone, elect and precious</hi> in Gods eies. I told him alſo, the gates of hel ſhould not prevaile againſt it; and all the power of Sathan ſhall be found weake a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it. And you haue thereby gathered, that it muſt be a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall, puiſſant, and invincible Empire. But <hi>Peter</hi> vnderſtood farre better this my ſtyle &amp; lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage; <hi>He that ſhall beleeue in it</hi> in this liuing Stone, in mee that am the Rocke of Iſrael, <hi>ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be confou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded.</hi> I had likewiſe ſaid vnto <hi>Peter, I will giue thee the keyes of the kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 22.</note> 
               <hi>whatſoever thou bindeſt on earth ſhall bee bound in heaven.</hi> And I gaue them indeede vnto him, &amp; vnto all his fellowes, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter my reſurrection; to wit, the miniſtrie of reconciliation by the preaching of the Goſpell. And thence you haue conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:13226:70"/>
               <hi>Thou art Peter; Ergo,</hi> the Biſhop of Rome is the vniverſal Biſhop of the world; hee ſhut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, and no man openeth, he o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peneth &amp; no man ſhutteth, Hee hath in his hands al power both temporall and ſpiritual, he ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth heaven, he ſhutteth hell, &amp; quencheth the fire in Purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, he commandeth the Angels hee keepeth in awe the Divels, he ſaveth or da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>neth men, at his owne pleaſure; he giueth diſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ations contrary to the lawe of God, and to his Goſpell; being not ſo much in the place of God as againſt God himſelfe. And yet are wee bound to beleeue, that God is changed in opinion when he is altered in his. But betweene theſe two propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; <hi>Thou art Peter,</hi> &amp; <hi>The Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Rome is <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ice-God,</hi> nay <hi>more then God.</hi> What a gulfe is there to be filled? And whence
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:13226:70"/>can it be filled, but fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomleſſe deepe? How much bet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter did the holy Apoſtle vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand this: <hi>Feed my ſheepe,</hi> that is with my word. <hi>Feed,</hi> ſaith he, you Prieſts my fellowes in the Prieſt hood, <hi>the flocke of Chriſt which is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted to your charge not as bearing rule over the inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance of the Lord,</hi> bee they of the Clergie or lay-men, <hi>but ſo, that ye may defend the flock. And whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the chiefe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhepheard ſhal ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, you ſhal receiue that incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible crowne of glory.</hi> And not here on earth a triple crown or kingdome. This therefore was the meaning of the Lord, farre different from thy gloſſe, &amp; yet <hi>Peter</hi> himſelf is the interpreter. And therfore would he haue an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſwered thee here, as before. <hi>Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the beginning it was not ſo.</hi> The firſt Biſhops of Rome, for the ſpace of 300. yeares, vnder the
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:13226:71"/>Heathe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Emperors, for the moſt part were all Martyrs, &amp; knewe neuer what this temporal iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction meant. As for the 400. years following, vnder the Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtian Emperours, they were hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſeruants; they obteined fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them their grants, immunities, and priuiledges, and helde as it were from them their chiefe au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority: ſo farre were they from once ſpeaking of giuing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, or making the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their feudarie vaſſals. As for the 300. enſuing yeares, they begin to embrace them, to vndermine them, &amp; by tricks &amp; ſmooth dealing defeat the one by an other; do at the length ſet themſelues in their place; they ſeaze vpon their dwellings, they put on their ſcarlet, inueſt themſelue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> with their crowne, ſet footing vpon their Empire, bewitch their ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iectes, and with their feete they
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:13226:71"/>ſpurne at their owne perſons. A long time after, and, as it were, through a long wood, come in by degrees the Iubilies, Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences, &amp; Faires or Markets of ſin, the bankes of Pardons; the <hi>Agnus Dei,</hi> the hallowd graines &amp; every day ſome new <hi>bables or others.</hi> In ſo much that for theſe 600. yeares and more, the moſt learned &amp; flouriſhing yeares of the Chriſtian church, ſhe could not looke ſo deepely into theſe myſteries, as to vnderſtand (eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Romiſh church it ſelfe, as much Latin as ſhe was) the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue &amp; force of theſe two Latin words; <hi>ecce duo gladij, Beholde here two ſwords.</hi> (What likelie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood is there in it?) Therfore he that vſeth them with both his handes at this day, though hee haue no other Miſſion, no other Commiſſion, yet ſhalbe vnto vs a Vice-God? And what elſe can
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:13226:72"/>he be, being he wil haue himſelf to be ſo, &amp; calleth himſelfe ſo, if he be it not?</p>
            <p>Thus therefore by this one word; <hi>Non ſic fuit ab initio. from the beginning it was not ſo,</hi> doeth our Lord here call vs backe to a reformatió of the abuſes of the church, in all hir partes, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his firſt inſtitution, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his word. And let theſe few pointes ſerue vnto vs for ſcantlings; as one beame of the Sunne; one drop of the Sea. You may after the like manner run over all the reſt. And would to God that in good time wee had practiſed this rule in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome; how many contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſchiſmes, wars, maſſacres, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſions, might we the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue ſpared &amp; avoided? of the which we are culpable, and hereafter muſt giue account. Whereas at the ſighes &amp; groanes of ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:13226:72"/>greate and holy perſons, throughout all Chriſtendome, for ſo many ages togither, wee haue out of pure pride only an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered them with this. <hi>It was impoſſible the church ſhould erre ſhee cannot erre.</hi> What conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence was there in this? And had not they the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cauſe enought to be leeue, that this was the voice of that woman in the Apocalypſe, <hi>I am a Queene, and ſhall never be a widdow?</hi> Say we therfore with the Prophet, <hi>Wee haue departed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy precepts &amp; from thy iudge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ments.</hi> Our Kings, our Prieſts,<note place="margin">Dan. 9. v. 5</note> our fathers, all our people; &amp; let vs not ſtand any longer vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our reputation, or thinke to maine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine our credit.<note place="margin">V. 7.</note> 
               <hi>Vnto thee belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth righteouſnes and vnto vs o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen ſhame,</hi> Vnto thee, ô Lord be the glory of our repentance, of our confeſſion, of our confuſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and of our ſhame; to the edifica<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:13226:73" rendition="simple:additions"/>of thy church, and the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our own ſouls, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>Soli Deo gloria.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>PAg.</hi> 18. <hi>lin.</hi> 4. <hi>for</hi> giueſt <hi>read</hi> giue. <hi>p.</hi> 31. <hi>l. vit. for</hi> cleane <hi>r.</hi> cleare. <hi>p.</hi> 42. <hi>l.</hi> 31 <hi>for</hi> connected <hi>r.</hi> converted. <hi>p</hi> 52. <hi>l.</hi> 22. <hi>for</hi> ſee <hi>r.</hi> ſet. <hi>p</hi> 58. <hi>l.</hi> 7. <hi>for</hi> extuberacie, <hi>r.</hi> an extuberancie <hi>p.</hi> 62 <hi>l</hi> 4 <hi>for</hi> they <hi>r.</hi> then. <hi>p.</hi> 67. <hi>l.</hi> 19. <hi>for</hi> vnprofitable <hi>r.</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitably. <hi>l.</hi> 21 <hi>for</hi> to our <hi>r.</hi> and to our <hi>p.</hi> 68. <hi>l.</hi> 8. <hi>for</hi> all <hi>r.</hi> already. <hi>p.</hi> 87. <hi>lin.</hi> 6 <hi>for</hi> take r. tooke <hi>p.</hi> 93. l 4. <hi>for</hi> rent <hi>r.</hi> rents.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:13226:73"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
